Well, hi Physionic community. Welcome
back to the Physionic Podcast, which is
my semianual,
semi- inconsistent podcast that I
release on particular topics that I find
especially interesting um that I've
covered over the last it's usually about
every six months or so. So, if you're
watching the video version of this, uh
you might notice that I'm semi outside
as well. That's because uh currently I'm
taking care of my mother who had uh
surgery. She's doing quite well. And um
I thought, you know, it's such a
beautiful day outside uh at at the house
that I might as well take an opportunity
to record outside for once. So, what are
we going to be covering in this episode,
which will be surely several hours long,
as they tend to be. I think, as I've
mentioned last uh last time, my record
is I think 5 hours. And I think I've got
only about 5 hours of recording on my
actual uh webcam. So, or on my
camcorder. So, it won't be lasting
longer than 5 hours. I can tell you that
much. Uh so the topics that we'll be
covering in this episode are bourberine
as an anti-olarctal cancer supplement,
five tests to
ascertain your health and to achieve
better health, try to improve those five
tests.
Then we'll be getting into restricting
glycine, that glycine that led to the
reversal of cancer.
I will be getting into my favorite
anti-aging hack
which will be highly relevant to uh
being outside. If you haven't seen that
analysis, I'll be covering my lithium
revisited which actually was not a very
popular topic, but it garnered a
significant blowback on me. So, I wanted
to cover some of the comments that were
uh thrown my direction as well as
obviously the the overall uh analysis
and the results and whatnot. Then I'll
be going over vitamin K against
cardiovascular disease. So, that was
another one of these analyses where I
got a lot of push back and uh some some
questions that I wanted to clarify as
well. I've also picked out some uh the
top comments uh under each one of those
particular videos on YouTube so that I
can address uh some of those as well.
And then I'll just be doing a little bit
of housekeeping. I
I'm going to leave it on a positive note
uh where I discuss a little bit of an
exchange that I have with Michael
Johnson. So, Michael, if you're uh I
don't know if you're watching this or
listening to this, um I'd like to kind
of highlight our conversation, which I
thought was rather lovely. So,
without further ado, I think we'll be
ready to go. I've got my Jovio mug right
here. I'm actually at the Jovio quote
unquote factory. So, if you're not
familiar with what Jovio is, it's my
dad's mug that he invented. I'm not
going to go into the whole spiel. If you
want to check it out, I'll put a link in
the description, but I'll be sipping on
this throughout. All right, so let's uh
let's get into bourbin as an
anti-olarctal cancer. Actually, before I
get on that, um I've turned off as many
ads as I possibly can. You know, all
these different media platforms. It
depends on which media platform you're
on, but they have their different
advertisement systems. Sometimes it's
fully automatic, so I can't do anything.
for YouTube. I have some control, not
complete control. So, turned off as many
ads as possible so that you're hopefully
not going to have an interrupted
sleeping experience. Uh, that said, I
think that's all I wanted to Oh, you can
also skip. I've got um I know that these
episodes are super long. Uh I will
supply timestamps so you can skip to
each section that you're interested in.
But uh also honestly if you want the
most in-depth then just check out the
actual analyses which are posted on
YouTube. I've got them on LinkedIn. I've
got them on I' I've actually started
posting on Instagram. I'll talk about
that a little bit later on. And
uh my free public community. I also
upload all the articles and videos there
as well. So if uh if you want access to
everything, you can literally just type
in the topic. So in this case, we're
going to be talking about bourbon and
colctal cancer and it should pop up in
my public community or my email list if
you're part of my email list. Again,
that's also free. Then you also get
everything just delivered to you. Okay,
that's it. That's that's enough of a
spiel. Let's get into it. Okay,
bourberin anti-ol colctal cancer. So, I
ran across this study that came out
in cell
I don't know if it was cell metabolism.
I don't think that it was but some sort
of cell adjacent journal. So, some
journal that is kind of a subcategory of
cell if I remember correctly. Don't
quote me on that. And within this study
which was a follow-up study if I
remember correctly I think yes that that
part is correct. So it was a follow-up
study of participants that had undergone
a randomized control trial where the
researchers had separated people to
placebo group or to consume bourberin.
The amount of bourberin since I'll cut
to that answer is 600 milligrams and it
was split in two. Uh for I said it I
think just like that and for some reason
a lot of people were confused. They
thought they were they were asking if it
was 600 mg twice. It is not. It's 600
milligrams. So 300 milligrams and 300
milligrams.
And so this group took bourberin for I
think a year or two in the initial study
and then for this cell follow-up study
uh what they did is they did a follow-up
where six years later they tracked if
people still had a reduced risk of
colurectal cancer and more specifically
they were looking at precancerous
growths. So they were looking at things
like
uh adenomas or some sort of abnormal
growth that was happening within the
colon. And so they did that for the
first two years in a randomized control
trial setting. And then after that it
was no longer technically randomized
control trial, but they did a follow-up
for an additional six years to see if
when people stop consuming bourbon, do
you still experience benefit? As in do
you still have reduced risk? Obviously
the way I'm talking you should know that
by now that in the randomized control
trial they showed that there was a
reduction in neoplasms and adinomomas
and these again these these are kind of
technical terms for abnormal growth that
are kind of precancerous and are on
their way to becoming cancerous becoming
colurectal cancer.
So in the first two years they found an
effect I think it was something like 20%
and then but then they had another
outcome that they were interested in in
figuring out uh more aggressive forms of
these adenomomas and uh numbers of these
adenomas and both of those were also
reduced I think it was on the order of
like 40 50% reduction compared obviously
this is relative to placebo
and then after the six years I'm just
going to repeat this one more time two
years on bourberine. Then they stopped
consuming bourbon. No longer on
bourberine. Six years later, they still
had reduced risk of these adenomas,
these these growths, these abnormal
growths in the colon. So this is pretty
exciting, right? Like that's that's a
pretty astounding finding. Now, of
course, there's always cautions with
these studies, right? The study was very
well done. I'm not I have nothing I have
nothing really negative to say about the
study. Um the study was pretty large for
a randomized control trial. Well, again,
these things are pretty expensive. But,
you know, even so, and I say this about
other supplements and other really just
any study, uh, when there's a single
study that comes out, I'm extremely
excited and I will report the data as it
is, but there's always a want for some
level of replication, right? We don't I
don't really want to to have this
assumption that it's going to carry
continuously.
So, we're still waiting for some sort of
replication. I say still waiting, I mean
it's been what, like four months since
the study released. So, it's uh it's
probably going to be a few years before
we have any sort of replication of this
study unless they're already working on
something. Um, which which could
certainly be the case. Uh, the same
thing is true for like GLAC when I
covered glycine and an acetylcysteine.
Those studies um that all those studies
come out of a single lab, right? They
come out of a very reputable lab, Baylor
Medicine research facility, which is
great, but that uh that doesn't mean
that we wouldn't like to see other
research groups come out because the
Gleak literature is just so like it's so
impressive what they were able to pull
off in in older individuals. So, the
same thing applies to this Bourburn
study. But I didn't want to leave it
just there, right? I wanted to cover uh
some of the mechanisms like how is
bourbon having this effect. So I did
find other studies by other research
groups that look at the mechanistic
relationship of bourberin on colctal
cancer. So these are studies where the
researchers are given or not the
researchers the participants are given
by the researchers uh bourberine or uh a
placebo and generally they focus more
not on like actual outcomes. So we're no
longer interested in outcomes at this
point like as in clinical outcomes I
should say. uh they're more interested
in
the
outcomes of like cell viability or uh
cancer growth like applying bourberine
to cancer cells that are taken from
humans or uh they apply it to mice that
are that have colorectal cancer uh or
are prone to colurectal cancer and then
doing a variety of different
measurements. So when it came to the
mechanisms, one of the mechanisms was a
reduced reduction in glucose uptake
inside the cancer cells. So when you
take uh these colctal cancer cells and
you apply bourberin to them and then you
measure for example the amount of
glucose that goes from outside of the
cell so the extracellular meu to the
actual inside of the cell. you can
measure that and what they found is that
when exposed to bourberine these cells
took up much less glucose and it was a
concentration dependent manner. So if
the more uh bourberine you added then
there was more and more reduction in the
cancer cell's ability to take up
glucose.
So that's certainly one possibility.
Now, of course, when you're looking at
in vitro work, which means that you're
looking at it with cells like what I
just described, actually applying
bourberine directly to the cells, uh,
you know, the the translation of that is
very difficult. So, there's always a
little bit of wiggle room there because
yes, that could be a mechanism, but the
amount of bourbon that we're consuming
is 600 milligrams. So, does that
translate to the level that's applied in
vitro? Is that what's actually being
delivered to the cancer cells? Um, and
often the answer is no. It's not going
to be a direct one to one, but at least
we know that bourberine isn't just
inert. It doesn't just do nothing to the
cancer cells. It does have direct impact
as in it reduces this glucose uptake. So
sugar uptake is reduced. So that's one
mechanism. The other mechanism or
another mechanism is that it changes the
microbiome uh to be less hospitable for
colurectal cancer. So for this this was
in uh mouse experiments if I remember
correctly.
where uh they applied bourberine or a
control substance to the mice. So they
fed them uh a control subst basically
regular chiao regular food. Uh or the
other group was given the chowo plus
bourberin in addition
and they showed that one obviously
colorectile cancer um occurrence was
lower in the bourberine group but in
addition to that uh they also showed
that the microbiome changes and uh they
specifically pinned it on a particular
bacterium. Now, I don't want to
want you coming away thinking that it's
only one bacteria. One bacteria is
causing all colorctal cancer. It's not
the case because of how strict the study
design is. They only looked at some
bacterium and they just focused in on
this one. Um, that doesn't mean that
there aren't many other factors that
also contribute, but they showed that
bourberine reduces this one bacterium
and this one bacterium is linked to
colctal cancer. And they show actually
if I I'm pretty sure this is correct
that uh when they exposed the mice that
were that were predisposed genetically
predisposed to colurectal cancer when
they exposed them to this bacterium that
they developed colctal cancer at a
faster rate. So there is a link between
this bacterium and I don't remember the
exact name. You'll have to go back to
the analysis and all that stuff. I don't
have that level of detail in my notes um
in front of me, but
the the big picture here, the big
takeaway here is that
bourberine has a direct impact on the
cells, the colctal cancer cells and it
also has a indirect effect on the
colorectal cancer cells by essentially
remove like changing the environment of
the colorectal cancer to be less
hospitable to the colctal cancer by
modulating the microbiome. the gut
microbiome. Okay. And then in the end
that leads to as you apply more bourbon
to these colctal cancer cells, their
cell viability decreases. And it's kind
of in a step-wise manner. So as you
increase your bourbon concentration,
there's a reduction in uh the the cells
can't live as in it's not just that they
don't take up as much glucose,
but they also just can't survive. they
undergo apoptosis which means programmed
cell death which is a good thing right
we want more of that when it comes to
cancer cells okay so let me take a step
back here because I I always try to be
as careful as I can be when
communicating this stuff this does not
mean that you should mega dose bourberin
I just need to pause there for a second
because people will understandable right
you hear oh well greater concentrations
of bourberin led to more cell cancer
cell death. So therefore, I will mega
dose bourberin,
but that's in an in vitro system. There
are no consequences for that, right?
You're just applying it to cells and
then you're seeing do the cancer cells
die? Yes. Great. Now you apply it to an
invivo system, an animal or to to us
humans
and I don't know, who knows? Maybe you
grow a third eye or you you know like
there's all kinds of different things
that could happen. So it's not it's not
a a immediate relationship where we jump
on as much bourburn as possible. The
only tested dose is 600 milligrams split
into two doses. Okay, just to just to be
clear on that. Okay, so that's where I
landed on bourbon and its anti-colctal
cancer mechanisms. Now, there were a few
comments. As I said, I pulled a few of
the top comments. Um,
some of them are kind of funny, like uh
I think it's spelled or pronounced shy
or sherry. C H Y R E. The auto captions
say borberin as in like kind of like
bourbon.
I conclude that this means bourberin and
Uh, too bad my preference is scotchin.
That's a good one. Um, I got so many of
different comments related to like the
captions saying bourbon or bourbon. I
just don't have the resources to go
through all my videos and just like
correct all the captions. That just
takes it's beyond me. Beyond me. Um, but
it does make for some some comedic
relief regardless. So, that was one
comment. Then Mike's
m i snz. These largely come from
YouTube, by the way. Is bourbon only for
colon cancer? What about other cancers?
So, that's a good question. The answer
is up to now all that I've seen that's
been of any convincing data, especially,
you know, having a throughine between
clinical data, uh, mechanistic data, and
maybe kind of in between of like
associative data, although I didn't
really look at that, uh, to to much
degree.
Uh the answer is it's only colorectal
cancer up to now. Um could there be
improvements you know in the future with
other types of cancers? Absolutely. Um
I'd like to see this these data be
reproduced but I'd also like to see
other types of cancers affected or see
if they're affected by bourberin. Now,
of course, with colurectal cancer,
there's an advantage, right? Because
colurectal cancer is right like when
when I was taught during my PhD,
the way we were taught is that the body
is if you were to split the body into
different sections and whatnot, the
internal and the external section quote
unquote of your body. Uh the way to
think about it is that your
gastrointestinal system, the actual
lumen as in the opening of your
gastrointestinal system from your mouth
being open like a tube down to your
stomach, the stomach then to your small
intestine, small intestine to the large
intestine, so on so forth, and then back
out your your anus.
That is all part of the exterior of your
body. Um, and the interior of the body
is where you have this barrier between
your blood system and the the this quote
unquote exterior of the body, this
tubing that that makes up your
gastrointestinal system. So the
advantage of bourberine is that you get
a direct impact and that's the same for
like fiber that's the same for really
any nutrient that has colctal cancer
effects is that we can directly attack
those colctal cancer cells because we're
getting a direct exposure or a very near
direct exposure to from the substance
that we consume
if that's a drug or if that's fiber or
if that's bourberin to the actual
colctal cancer. So, it's much easier to
target. Um, and it wouldn't surprise me
if we were able to just in general
target those cancer cells much easier
than we can uh other cancer cells. On
the flip side, well, let me finish that
thought. So, on the difficulty is that
then for others like breast cancer
that's inside the body, right? That
again quote unquote inside the body.
It's I'm not saying like technically
people could easily argue okay my
gastrointestinal system sure the tubing
might be quote unquote outside the body
but in reality it's still affecting me
right and that's a fair point but the
way it was taught I'm just pointing that
out so if we go back to the inside of
the body it has to pass this this
epithelial layer the actual
gastrointestinal system if you were to
use a drug or bourberine or whatever it
might be has to go into the bloodstream
has to travel the bloodstream and end up
at the site of cancer. So if you're
talking about breast cancer, brain
cancer, brain cancer is even more
difficult because you've got this uh
this special layer that separates uh the
other parts of the body from the brain
as well. Uh bone cancer, whatever it
might be, muscle cancer, uh there's
there's all kinds of different barriers
that the drug has to get through and
then it has to target to those
particular areas which makes it
ultimately that much more difficult. Now
the one negative of colorectal cancer is
it's actually surrounded by epithelial
cells. So if you have a growth of these
abnormal cells that you know these
cancer cells that are obviously fast
dividing the other cells in that area
also fast dividing you you're constantly
recycling through these epithelial cells
that make up your intestinal lining. So
it does make things pretty tricky. Uh
right because now you're trying to
target this colorectal cancer and you
can directly target it. That's great.
But what happens to the other cells that
also behave a lot like cancer cells?
They're not cancer cells. But and you
don't really want to attack those,
right? Because those cells are actually
serving a purpose. So there's there's
always trickery. There's always
difficulty when it comes to uh cancer
research and that's that's what makes it
uh just such a difficult disease to deal
with on multiple fronts beyond what I'm
discussing here. So Mikeson's uh the
answer is currently only for colurectal
cancer as far as I've been able to find.
Okay, the next topic is five tests for
better health. This came about from a
centrifuge episode, which I've been
having a ton of fun making these uh
centrifuge episodes, which if you
haven't seen any of those episodes, uh
they are
in simple terms a centuge. What it does
is that it spins out one thing from
another thing. And the idea behind the
centerfuge episodes that I release on
for physionic is that we're separating
out the BS from the truth. Uh the
reality, the sciencebacked information.
So
what I do is I take health podcasts,
health shows, and I
I used to want to do like the entire
podcast that I can't express to you how
much work goes into some of these
episodes. uh because I'm trying to be as
accurate as possible and I try to be
give as much leeway as possible
because I also don't want to be seen as
unfair.
So
when a person says I don't know it can
be some some like small comment I have
to spend hours trying to fact check that
one small comment which is like what 30
seconds for them to just say it and then
it's hours for me to have to go back and
make sure that that comment is correct
and I can know the answer right I can
know the answer but the point of the
centeruge is not for me to pit my
credentials against somebody else's
credentials. That's that's just that's
just relying on authority
as opposed to what the point is is for
me to show you, okay, here we've got
evidence and here we have no evidence or
we have evidence against that claim.
Right? That's the point. It's not for
for us to rely on Nick has a PhD
therefore he is correct. That's not the
point.
So anyway,
the centerfuge episodes take a really
long time, but that's not what we're
here to discuss. The reason why I'm
mentioning that is because I did a two I
think two centerfuge episodes on Dr.
Casey Means. Uh Dr. Casey Means is
a she has her doctorate in medicine.
I don't think that she's practicing. I'm
pretty sure she's not practicing. Uh,
and I believe she dropped out of a
residency near the end of her residency,
but anyway, she she's put out some a lot
of different content. She has this book
uh I don't remember the name of it but
she has a at least one book that's out
and she was making this podcast tour and
she was on the J Shetty podcast and in
that podcast she was talking about what
five tests would free or preferably free
tests she would suggest that anybody get
to make sure that they are uh above
board on their health like their health
is is doing Well,
so her list, I'm going to go through her
list first. Her list was fasting
glucose, so fasting blood sugar,
triglycerides, blood fats,
HDL cholesterol, that's the third one.
Fourth is waist circumference, and then
finally blood pressure. Okay. So then I
went through and I picked out you know I
went through these five and I did a
bunch of research did you know found
different studies from different uh
universities and different um different
systems different governing bodies and
whatnot and try to corroborate you know
what the correct reference ranges were.
if this particular
uh factor, this particular test was the
mo the the most recommended uh based on
the most current literature. And there
were some inconsistencies. I'll just put
it this way. So, for a lot of it, she
was spot on. And keep in mind that this
is free or just about free. I mean
really the the main focus was it on
being free as in it's covered by your
insurance and you don't need uh to to
get a special additional test added on.
So this is from a basic blood panel that
you would get from like your physical
your yearly physical. So fasting glucose
is a good one. Um it's not as good and I
know people mention this well what about
HBA1C or some of these other measures
that would be better? What about
insulin? Um, and that's all fair. That's
that's all true, but usually I know some
people were saying, "Well, HBA1C is
really cheap where I am." Still, that's
an additional cost. That's an additional
test on top of your basic blood panel.
Uh, for most people, at least that's
been my experience. That's been
experience that I've seen across the
board on like LabCore or if you do Quest
Diagnostics or any of those. So, I think
blood sugar is fine. Uh, fasting
glucose, the number for that. So I'm
going to give you the numbers is less
than 100 milligrams per deciliter. That
would be considered uh in within the
healthy range. Anything above that
you're getting into pre-diabetes and
diabetes obviously if you go far above
that. Okay. The next one was
triglycerides.
And triglycerides
was an interesting one.
It's not that I necessarily disagree
with that one. It's just that there's
much less importance that's placed on
triglycerides. And she did make an she
did make a point in one of the episodes
that the reason why we don't focus on
something like triglycerides
is because we we can't or we don't have
a drug to treat it. So that's why it's
kind of fallen out of favor. And I have
to say I completely disagree with her on
that. um the I didn't know. So, first
off, I didn't know the answer. I didn't
know like I knew that triglycerides had
kind of fallen out of favor. I'm not
saying that it has no importance, but
it's definitely not one of like the the
main ones that you should definitely be
checking. Um the reason why it's quote
unquote fallen out of favor is because
there have been drugs that have actually
been implemented and tested and whatnot
and they showed no impact.
So, I don't know about you, but like
if I'm a pharmaceutical company and I
create a drug and I test it in thousands
of people and then I see no benefit,
how like first of all, the FDA is just
going to laugh in your face. They're
going to be like, "Absolutely not.
You're not allowed to release this." Um,
but secondly, why would I continue to
invest money into that, right? Like,
what's what's the point? And beyond
that, a lot of the other research that's
come out that's not drugrelated, that's
just shown like links with
triglycerides, when you control for
other factors like uh particle number of
of LDL particles or VLDLDL particles or
just apo in general, suddenly
triglycerides play much lower if any
role whatsoever. Um, and I'll explain
that a little bit more in in just a
little bit. Uh but for now just know
that triglycerides are not very high up
on the list. Um I'm not saying that so
for example
if you have diabetes
there's a chance a pretty good chance
that your triglycerides are really high
but does that mean that you should
target your triglycerides specifically?
The answer is probably not. You should
target the diabetes as a whole and that
will probably reduce your triglycerides.
Uh, but if you were to target your
triglycerides but still have diabetes,
guess what? You're probably still pretty
screwed. Sorry to say. But, you know, to
put it bluntly, you you should focus on
the the the thing that has the most
evidence, which nobody would dispute
that diabetes is going to shorten your
lifespan, inc massively increase your
risk of mortality, cardiovascular
disease, all kinds of different factors.
So, that should be the focus. Okay. All
right. The next one that she mentions is
HDL cholesterol. And I just happened to
do a full analysis on HDL cholesterol.
And this is a similar story. Um, in
fact, it's I think even even more of a
story than it is with triglycerides
where triglycerides there could be some
arguments made, but HDL cholesterol is
so to describe what HDL cholesterol is.
Uh, you've probably heard of LDL
cholesterol, uh, low density lipoprotein
cholesterol. This is high density
lipoprotein cholesterol, HDL. And LDL
has been linked to cardiovascular
disease across many many different
studies to varying levels of strength.
And there's multiple reasons for that.
But the focus on HDL,
she mentions this focus on HDL. And
maybe about 20 years ago,
researchers and physicians and the
governing bodies and whatnot. When I say
governing bodies, I'm talking about like
the society of lipidology or uh the
European society of atherosclerosis,
you know, like those kinds of governing
bodies. Um
they have you so 20 years ago or so they
did mention yeah having higher HDL is a
good thing to have and low HDL can be is
linked to all these different disease
states diabetes cardiovascular disease
all those different uh disease states.
However,
re in the last like 10 years, 5 to 10
years, pharmaceutical companies, the
ones with a ton of money, obviously
they're trying to make money, right? Uh
so they developed these drugs and they
thought, okay, well, if HDL, if
increasing HDL is what we need to do to
improve health outcomes, then that's
what we should do. we should focus on
HDL. So they developed several drugs, I
think like three, at least three
different drugs from different
pharmaceutical companies that targeted
HDL and and and kind of artificially
increased HDL independent of everything
else or at least that was the idea. And
they showed repeatedly there was no
effect. So if you increase HDL but keep
everything else the same and then you
compare to another group of people that
do not raise HDL and they also have
every everything else the same. So
talking about LDL, talking about blood
sugar, talking about insulin levels,
talking about let's say triglycerides,
talk about your general health, they're
not diabetic, all that stuff. All
everything else is the same across both
groups being compared, but one group has
this drug that, you know, increases
their HDL.
There's no difference in mortality,
cardiovascular events whatsoever. So
that's one huge line of evidence. But of
course, there are problems with that,
right? Like there there's possibility
that the drug has offtarget effects. And
in fact, there was one drug that did
have offtarget effects that ultimately
led to more deaths as in its offtarget
effects. It's its side effects led to
more deaths, which is obviously
horrifying. And that they stopped that
trial and they said, "Okay, I think
we'll we'll back away from that one. I
think uh I think we'll pass." um which
is what they should do because again if
you were to try to push that through the
FDA they would laugh in your face. They
would say absolutely not. We won't even
we won't even entertain the discussion.
So
then but then there were some drugs that
did not seem to have any side effect or
I shouldn't say didn't have any side
effects but compared to placebo didn't
have any extremely detrimental side
effects that would affect the outcome
and ultimately they still didn't show a
benefit. Okay. So but that's still one
line of evidence that still doesn't
necessarily mean that uh we should do
away with HDL. What about all these
correlational studies that showed that
HDL was linked higher HDL was linked to
better cardiovascular disease mortality
and whatnot? Well, again, there were
other studies that were done after that,
you know, adjusting for some of the new
information that we knew, like for
example, APOB levels um and looking at
blood sugar, insulin, etc., etc. And
suddenly the the effect was far more
muted. There is still a relationship
between extremely high HDL like over a
100 milligrams per deciliter verse and
very low HDL like I don't know like 20
milligrams per deciliter and how there's
still there's kind of this U-shaped
curve where people that are very low or
very high still have increased risk of
mortality but mortality is kind of a
dirty metric right it's a good metric in
general like it's informative but it's
Not it's not as informative as people
like to scream about which sometimes I
get comments people saying well let's
just look at mortality
uh overall total mortality all cause
mortality that's the only thing that
matters well okay let me ask you this
how would you determine the difference
between a drug that has an effect it
improves cardiovascular disease right so
therefore mortality would decrease total
mortality would decrease as a result of
improvement ments in cardiovascular
mortality. But what if that drug
increase cancer mortality?
Now if those are roughly equal in the
number of people that they save lives on
the cardiovascular disease mortality but
they increase the risk of cancer
mortality the same number of people
roughly the same number of people die
from cancer
that the total mortality
benefit would be neutral. So now you've
lost the nuances of that measure, right?
So that's why I and this is like I is
something that's really important for
people to understand. Just looking at
mortality
is not the end all beall just because
you don't see changes. And there's other
reasons why you shouldn't just look at
mortality. Now to be clear, I still love
mortality data. That sounds that's
honestly that sounds awful. Um, I don't
mean it, and I know you understand that.
I don't mean it as like, yeah, people
died. That's definitely not my point.
Um, it's it's awful that people died,
but I'm just talking about the data
itself, the the actual outcome itself is
fantastic, except it has shortcomings
and and those can be addressed by by
being more specific about what you're
looking at. If you expect something to
improve cardiovascular disease
mortality, then that is what you should
look at. You can also look at total
mortality. But don't be shocked if total
mortality does not budge, but
cardiovascular disease specific
mortality does budge or cancer
mortality, whatever it might be. So I
just wanted to quick point that out. So
with HDL there is still this like
U-shaped curve where really low or
really high like absurdly high levels uh
is linked but that that doesn't
necessarily mean that it's causing
and that's where we're getting into a
whole new phase of understanding HDL
because now we're starting to look at
the particle quality and that's
something that uh I discussed a little
bit for the insiders in my my analysis
but we're still pretty early on in
understanding particle quality and its
relationship to uh cardiovascular
disease and just health in general. So
that's the second line of evidence. We
we started looking more at the
correlational evidence and we started
adjusting for more things that we
understood tracked that actually caused
cardiovascular mortality and suddenly
the relationship weakened significantly.
And then there was a third line of
evidence where if you looked at the
Mandelian randomization trials, which is
essentially people where their genetics
indicate that they have elevated HDL
that is independent of anything else. So
they are automatically randomized. So
they're randomly assigned to having high
HDL or not having high HDL because of
their genetics. And we can look at the
relationship that that gene has to other
uh other molecules, other factors. And
if we isolate to just the genes that we
are reasonably confident only affect HDL
and we just look at those groups of
people versus the people that have
normal genes, quote unquote normal genes
and don't have this elevated level of
HDL, then we can compare over a lifetime
if the people with high HDL have an
abnormal protection from cardiovascular
disease. And the answer is no. So again,
uh there's no difference between the two
groups over a lifetime of having
elevated HDL. So we've got three lines
of evidence and we've got more, but
those are three massively powerful I
mean that's like huge amounts of
information telling us that HDL is not
what you should be targeting.
So hopefully I've somewhat explained and
convinced you that HDL is not something
that you should be super focused on. I'm
not saying it has no importance, but it
should be pretty low on the list. Okay,
the next one was waist circumference.
She mentions waist circumference. I
think this is a good one, right? Like,
so it's a it's a proxy metric for, you
know, being overweight, being over fat,
uh having high visceral fat. I think
this one's perfectly fine. And then, of
course, blood pressure. Uh I think she
threw out some numbers that were above
what the standard recommendations are
currently.
the recommendations I guess hold on let
me go back to waist circumference waist
circumference the the numbers
were below 40 in or 102 cm for men and
35 in or below 88 cm for women. Okay. Uh
blood pressure
was the the current recommendations are
below 120 over 80. So 120 systolic which
is the top number and then 80 uh as the
bottom number. And there are many many
many many many studies that show that if
you reduce your blood pressure there is
a point you know where it could be
dangerous. But like if you're anywhere
like 110 or even 100 or 120 you're
you're not there's not much risk there.
But if obviously if you're going like
way way below that then you know there
may be a conversation to be had with
your physician. But as it stands, uh,
having blood pressure in like the 140s
and comparing that to people that have
their blood pressure in the 120s, no
matter how you reduce it, if that's
through lifestyle or if that's through
drug intervention or whatever it might
be, or if the supplements, whatever,
okay, we'll just we'll just move on.
We'll just say sure, whatever. Whatever
the reason is, whatever the intervention
is, you use it and it drops your blood
pressure, you are far better off and you
will have uh improved or reduced
cardiovascular disease risk.
Now, let me circle back using that good
old consulting speak. Let me circle back
to the HDL. Okay, so my list did change.
My list was different. my list again
with the caveat that these have to be
largely free or covered by insurance
uh basic insurance or like something you
would get at a physical. So fasting
glucose is fine like yes would I love to
have you know more information like
HBA1C or insulin levels all that stuff?
Yes, for sure. But as it stands, fasting
glucose, triglycerides, like I I was
having a tough time really figuring out
one to maybe replace that with. Maybe
you could make an argument for like C
reactive protein, um, CRP,
but triglycerides are fine
if you know how to think about them in
relationship to the next one that I'll
mention. So, because I said HDL is not
that great of a marker, HDL cholesterol,
let's remove that one and let's put in
honestly it's exact opposite nonHDL
cholesterol. Non-HDL cholesterol is a
measure of the cholesterol. So, remember
how I said low density lipoproteins, so
LDL and HDL, so high density
lipoprotein. Well, there are others,
right? They're intermediate density
lipoproteins and they're very low
density lipoproteins and those get all
combined into your total cholesterol. So
the actual cholesterol that's found
inside of these particles.
So if you measure the total cholesterol
and then you subtract the HDL
cholesterol then you're left with only
the LDL, the LDL and the VLDL. So these
these kind of major components of
cholesterol that are in your
bloodstream,
then that gives you an indication of
your risk because those do track and
have been shown over and over to cause
cardiovascular disease. So, it's still
not a perfect metric, but it tends to be
better than just looking at something
like LDL cholesterol, which LDL
cholesterol
has some association and some
relationship and is causitive, but
because it's not pime, it's not the only
factor.
It's not as good of a marker as
something like nonHDL cholesterol. So
that's why I say non-HDL cholesterol
which the metric or the the range for
that should be less than 130 milligrams
per deciliter.
Now another thing that I'll quick point
out is that some people pointed out and
I I was okay with waist circumference
but some people were saying well what
about waist to hip ratio which which can
give you a more uh more targeted
approach can give you a more uh exact
answer. And I think that's that's a
really good uh that's a really good
suggestion. Waist to hip ratio the pro
the only problem with it is that it's
less common. We have less data on it.
And although when compared from my
understanding which I haven't done a
deep dive on this but from my
understanding is when you do compare it
against waist circumference alone there
is a better predictive ability of waist
to hip ratio. Um, however, that doesn't
that doesn't necessarily mean that you
have to do waist to hip ratio. You can
still do waist circumference and get a
lot of really important information. But
considering that it's free and you could
do it, I think there's some measurement
error that could happen because when
you're measuring the hips compared to
the waist, um, you know, that could
introduce some error, but yes, waist to
hip ratio is a is a perfectly reasonable
uh
alternative to waist circumference. And
of course, blood pressure is fantastic.
So, my list, fasting glucose,
triglycerides, I would put it probably
at the very bottom of that list. And I
might even switch that out for a C
reactive protein because it might tell
you some more information related to
other issues that may be going on that
are not necessarily cardiovascular
disease, non-HDL cholesterol for sure,
waist circumference or waist to hip
ratio, fine, and blood pressure. Those
would be my five. And of course there
are better tests that are out there as
well that you can do for if you want to
pay extra or do more uh with that. Okay.
So comments
uh William Light had this to say. Uh I
was chief resident. I taught interns and
residents the details of how to
interpret laboratory results. This is
not taught in medical school, but you
learn how to practice and such during
internship and residency. Okay. So why
is William talking about this? William
is talking about this because Dr. Casey
means made a a a quick comment saying
that uh doctors are not taught how to
interpret uh medical result shouldn't
say medical results blood lab results
which I did find incredibly peculiar.
Uh but
my understanding is that keep in mind
I'm a PhD. So I went to medical school
for my PhD, not for my actual hands-on
uh you know blood testing and all that
stuff. Uh so like a clinician would, a
physician would. Uh so I don't have any
firsthand experience to to be able to
speak to that. I can say from firsthand
experience during my master's program
during kinesiology, exercise physiology,
we did have to do blood draws and we had
to do um analysis of like lab results.
We had to do EKGs. We had to do all that
stuff. So we were taught I can say that
much. Um but I just can't speak
necessarily for physicians. But I'm I'm
hardpressed to say to like I find it
very strange that a physician would not
be trained in medical school
how to read lab results or what lab
results mean. Um William is saying
something kind of in the middle right uh
saying that okay it might be true that
we were not taught in medical school but
you are taught somewhere along your
medical journey. So, uh, before you
become an attending, you will be
educated on these different lab results
and whatnot, which is fair enough. I
still find it really hard to believe. I
mean, look, again, I I don't have any
firsthand experience, so I can't say.
Um, and if you're a doctor and you're
listening to this, I'd be curious if you
had learned about your like just lab
results in general, how to read lab
results in medical school or was it
later? Was it actually in your residency
that you learned that? And regardless,
it doesn't really matter because
ultimately you can't uh as far as I'm
aware, you can't get like an actual job
and and and practice with patients
without having gone through some level
of additional training after medical
school. So, um yeah, I'd just be
interested in in your take, but thank
you for commenting, William.
Uh, DAB R1
had this to say. I want to be proactive
in addressing health concerns and I like
a and I like a lot of these influencer
types because they focus on prevention,
nutrition, exercise, sleep, etc. These
are big categories that we know are
important. However, there are a lot of
specifics where I have big questions.
Eg. supplements, fasting, very specific
timing for eating and exercise where you
could do a lot of good by checking for
evidence. Thank you for this series. I
appreciate it. Um, and thank you. Yeah.
So,
yeah, the influencer types.
I I mean, I've I've I could probably
talk about this topic for hours. Um
the influencer types, yes, they do they
do
put a lot of focus on sleep and exercise
generally uh
and the basics which I I do appreciate
and I think that there are certain areas
especially with the different stories
that I've heard that you know some
physicians I don't I certainly don't
want to alienate physicians as a whole
some physicians you know don't put
enough emphasis on some of these
lifestyle factors that you can improve.
Um and there are multiple reasons,
myriad reasons for for that.
So the influencers coming in and saying
like oh you know focus on your sleep and
and make sure you know there's research
saying that you can improve like if you
do highintensity interval training that
can be extremely beneficial for
cardiovascular health or uh your the age
of your heart and things of that nature.
Then yeah I think I think from that
perspective absolutely I think that uh
health influencers have been a positive
in that regard. I think the tricky part
is
where we start getting into more
speculative categories like supplements
uh like
fasting, let's say, or specific timing
of eating like you mentioned.
That's where
you're starting to rely on much smaller
trials because they just or much smaller
studies.
So you'll rely on studies of like 12
people in the placebo group and like 14
people in the intervention group.
Meanwhile, the pharmaceutical companies
can pull together like 3,000 people for
their trial. So they, you know, so we're
we're and I do this, right? Like I still
cover those studies. Um, but it's it's
always a bit of a cautious story
because with small studies, you know, is
it really can you broadly apply it to
everyone? Probably not, right? But we
just don't have those nuances because
they're just isn't the money to to be
able to to actually do those trials to
do the trials on the level of the
pharmaceutical industry. Um, and the
pharmaceutical pharmaceutical industry,
they they definitely have a lot of
really high quality studies that are out
there. Um, you know, let's put aside the
fact, you know, the the whole like
funding and like the bias and whatnot.
Um, I know people some people are kind
of on a on a spectrum in relation to
their their level of trust related to
the FDA and pharmaceutical industry and
whatnot. And that's fair. I But I'm not
going to go down that rabbit hole. But
if you're looking at small studies,
suddenly you're you're like, "Okay, so
they found an effect." Great. But, you
know, is it powered enough to to really
determine if there are serious side
effects? Did it run long enough? You
know, all these different things that
would be required of the pharmaceutical
industry. They are required if they're
going to offer a drug to do multiple
studies on that drug to have
increasingly large sample sizes to
invest millions and millions and
millions of dollars into something. Um
and then they have to present that data
to the FDA. They have to to give over
their data. um the FDA has a very
specific um set of criteria that the
pharmaceutical industry has to meet and
so you know with pretty good certainty
because the FDA is pretty strict about a
lot of things when it comes to the
packages that are delivered um how the
pharmaceutical industry packages their
their information all that stuff.
But with supplements or with fasting
studies or any of that stuff, you you
don't have those restrictions. There are
there's no FDA sitting there saying,
"Oh, well, you didn't do the the fasting
experiment a certain way, so therefore,
you know, you can't do it or we're not
going to approve it or whatever it might
be." Um because they're just not focused
on that kind of stuff. Um we have
what's it called? inter I think it's
called internal review boards IRB
where they'll they'll they will so you
have a panel of people that will assess
if a study should be allowed to be
conducted in the first place for ethical
reasons. Are there, you know, potential
safety considerations or ethical
considerations that need that, you know,
restrict a study design or whatever it
might be? And that's obviously
incredibly valuable to have and that's
we absolutely have to have that.
But, you know, on the back end, you
know, are you going to get
front end and back end, are you going to
get, you know, billions of dollars to
study like even a super popular
supplement like creatine? uh from
different different avenues.
Like for example, creatine like there's
tons of uh research on creatine and
muscle and you know uh performance and
whatnot. But now we're discovering okay
maybe there's a potential that it could
help our brain as well.
But you know that started with like
pretty pretty small studies and then
we've we've kind of built onto that
literature and just continued to come
out with these different trials. But
it's not like because for example the
pharmaceutical industry they know that
there's no special creatine formula that
they can patent and then make a ton of
money on. So of course that aspect of
the pharmaceutical criticism is
definitely true where of course they're
not going to invest millions of dollars
into creatine and creatine research um
because
it's pretty cheap to get and you just
get the cheapest version, right? you
just get creatine monohydrate. So, are
you going to get the funding for like a
study with 5,000 people in it where they
look at like brain health with creatine
supplementation and they look at, you
know, primary outcomes, secondary
outcomes, they look at side effects, all
that stuff like no, right? You're not
going to get that. Um, so that's where I
think the reason why I'm mentioning all
this is that I think that's where the
influencers they they kind of make these
false equivalencies of like the drugs
that are out there saying that the
supplement has just as much evidence.
And sometimes, and I think for nefarious
reasons, I think sometimes we demonize
drugs and focus so much attention on
supplements and
because
we we're trying to like create this
narrative like the the drugs, the
pharmaceutical companies, um
they're they're only creating damaging
things. They're only creating this
profitering kind of mentality, which
there's some truth to the whole profit
aspect, right? Like I mentioned, they're
not going to fund studies that they
can't make money off this particular
molecule. Fair enough. But
we also can't be communicating about
supplements and whatnot, most
supplements, as if they have the same
level of evidence that a lot of these
drugs have behind them. And
that's where health influencers really
just make these false equivalencies or
again they just downgrade the drugs. Oh,
don't worry about the drug. Yeah, pharma
that's bad. But this drug, this
supplement
on the other hand is topnotch. We have
two studies in 13 people, you know, and
it's like, dude, you you if you were to
stack those two together, you it it is
ridiculous how much effort and data is
on the drug and how little is on the
supplement. Um,
and I I honestly I think I probably need
to do a better job of that myself. It's
not to say that the supplements don't
work, but people are so focused on
supplements
and so they want to know more about the
supplements. They want to know more
about the fasting. They want to know
more about just basically anything
alternative to the things that have been
rigorously tested over and over and over
again. Um, which you know again is fair
and there's a lot of excitement there
and I get excited about certain
molecules like the Bourberine thing for
example. That's why I always point I try
to point out like hey we have one study
or Galinac. Uh we've got multiple
studies but they all come out of one
lab. Um
and the effect size is huge for like
GLAC. Like it's pretty remarkable. I'm
still a pretty like big fan. I'm just
kind of cautious about the fact that we
it's all out of one lab. Uh so and it
doesn't go through this like special
testing and all that stuff. So yeah,
I'll I'll close it with this. Just
health influencers, yes, they've had
some positive impact. I just
think that sometimes it gets pushed
beyond the positive and it definitely
turns into a negative and it can create
a lot of uncertainty and
it creates a lot of false
equivalency between like you know
different supplements saying oh well
this works for this and this works for
this and this works for that and now we
can stack all these supplements and it's
like we don't have any evidence evidence
that you can stack these four things
together and suddenly you'll just be
better off than if you had done this
other thing that's got tons of research
behind it, but it's just not as sexy.
Um,
but you know, we as humans just like to
be, you know, for some people, they just
want to be cutting age. They want to be
the the person telling everybody, "Yeah,
I'm taking green leaf extract out of a
monkeykey's butthole, and it's just like
the best thing in the world." You you
got to stop the ozic. You got to stop
the statins. You got to you know that's
that's old news, man. It's all pharma
stuff. Monkey butthole green leaf
extract. That's that's going to be the
new frontier. Uh meanwhile, if the
pharmaceutical companies sniffed even
for a moment that that worked, they'd be
on it. They would be on it. Um, and you
know, there's certain certainly
discoveries like the uh the new I'm
gonna pronounce it correctly this time,
reta tride
uh peptide, which I have more content
coming out soon uh on I mean that I
think that I'm pretty sure that was at
least partly funded by public funding,
so NIH funding. And that is I mean that
is an incredible peptide. Uh I mean I'm
sure there's going to be side effects
with it because it's so potent. Um but
in terms of the effect related to side
effects like aside from the the the
normal side effects that you experience
with a lot of these like different uh
GLP-1 receptor agnus peptides
which are gastrointestinal discomfort uh
nausea maybe vomiting and whatnot which
isn't fun. Let's like we need to
acknowledge that that's not fun. Um, but
if you dose it correctly, like reta
trutide has some incredible like some
effects that are beyond what we've ever
seen before. And I'm very excited to
cover that. So definitely look for that.
I've already finished my uh research
into that. I've already done all the the
notes for my video and all that. So I'll
in the article and I'll I'll put all
that out in uh several weeks. So
yeah, there's there's definitely
discoveries that we're making that are
kind of unexpected and then, you know,
uh pharmaceutical industry jumps on it
and tries to figure out a way to patent
it, right, to make money. Uh but
ultimately it still leads to significant
benefit. So um yeah, it's just I I'll
get off this, like I said, I could talk
about this for hours. I've got many
opinions uh on the topic, but I'll I'll
leave it there. Um, in short, health
influencers have done some good. They've
also done some negative. Uh, and
in terms of supplements, fasting, very
specific timing and all that. Yeah. I
mean, I'm going to continue to cover
that stuff because that's what people
want. People want I mean, I have to
follow what people want to a degree. Uh,
but I also, you know, I have to always
check myself and make sure that I'm
doing it responsibly. Uh because telling
that information like you want to weave
a story, you want to get people excited,
but you also want to hit them with like
honest truth like hey look uh this is a
study in 12 people or there's no placebo
group here or I don't know any number of
different things like we don't have
safety data on this like this was in a
mouse like whatever it might be. So you
have to be honest with with that kind of
stuff too. Okay, the next topic ladies
and gentlemen is glycine. Restricting
glycine led to a reversal of cancer.
Okay, this was a hot topic. Uh so there
was this phase one clinical trial that
released I believe in December maybe
November and I covered it in December
and in this study they showed this was a
cell metabolism study.
They showed that people that were put on
a specialized diet where
they
ate basically no glycine and basically
no serarine. So those are two amino
acids
that
they experienced significant reversal of
cancer. And there was this really punchy
image of this person with colurectal
cancer had this massive tumor
and after being placed on this diet and
it was actually I think only like nine
weeks.
So after 9 weeks
they they showed the image of that same
tumor that same site and it was just
gone which is just like what
just by restricting two amino acids. Of
course this is with amunotherapy. So
basically all cancer research you're
almost never going to get research
that's just like hey what happens if we
just restrict this one amino acid? Good
luck. Hope you don't die. Um it's it's
definitely going to be here's our
standard protocol and then on top of
that would you be interested in trying
something novel something new to see
novel new I just said the same thing to
see if um if that could have additional
benefit and of course it would help
scientists and if there's any sort of
harm that we you know detect that
there's some sort of harm we'll stop of
course because again ethics uh
incredibly important So
they showed that when these people it
was it wasn't a big trial right it's
phase one so uh these people were on
this restrictive diet some of them were
on for only 3 weeks some of them were on
for six weeks some of them were on for
the full nine weeks and they showed that
there was for most people at least some
regression in cancer and some people
were able to see huge decreases in
tumors like tumor size to essentially it
being undetectable um by the the by
visual by the eye. Okay, so cool.
That's pretty that's pretty impressive.
I mean that's actually I would say
incredibly impressive. But then of
course because glycine is such a popular
supplement
people were and I knew this was going to
happen. So I added in my initial
analysis I said does this mean that you
should stop supplementing glycine? The
answer is no. So that seems weird right
to say well hold on if I restrict
glycine I get rid of cancer but I
shouldn't restrict glycine. I should
keep supplementing with glycine. Okay so
the reason why I mentioned that was
multiple reasons. Initially it was for
one main reason. And then that reason
grew into multiple other reasons as I
went over some more literature. So the
answer was that
one if you don't have cancer then this
doesn't apply to you right like we're
talking about we're talking about a
pathology. So in that situation if you
don't have cancer then supp you know
continue supplementing with glycine.
There are multiple studies indicating
benefits. I went over gleac a little bit
um and there are others as well. So no
reason to stop for that. It's not at no
point was there a claim by the
researchers or by me that glycine causes
cancer. Like if you increase your
glycine intake that now you you are more
likely to develop cancer. So no one was
saying that. So for the vast majority of
people cool. Then even if you have
cancer,
now we've got two amino acids that were
restricting at the same time. And people
could argue, well, they should have only
restricted one. Well, you have limited
resources and you have to make a choice.
And based off of the pre-clinical data
that had been done before that, they had
restricted both amino acids. So, they
can't get to the clinical data and be
like 5050, guys. You know, maybe it's
the maybe it's both have to be
restricted. Maybe it's just one that has
to be restricted. Like, are we going to
take a gamble and guess like which one
we're going to restrict and just kind of
hope that it does something? Um, no.
They just followed what the pre-clinical
data did and they translated it to
humans. So, they restricted searing and
they restricted glycine at the same
time. So, even if a person has cancer,
like we can't jump to any conclusion. We
can't say, "Oh, well,
uh, yeah, you should stop glycine." This
is a phase one trial. There's no control
group. Uh, so we don't know what would
happen if we controlled for people that
were just on the imunotherapy. This
included multiple types of cancer,
colurectal, breast, like a bunch of
different types of cancer. And it was
very heterogeneous. So, as in like some
people experienced significant
improvements and other people did not
experience improvements as in some
people still progressed in their cancer.
The problem is we don't have a control
group. So, we don't know if they
progressed slower in their cancer than
people that were in the control group
because there was no control group. So
many different questions. So, we don't
change behavior based off of early data.
I mean that is a risk that you as an
individual can take but no physician and
I'm not a physician but I wouldn't say
oh now just start start cutting all your
glycine because uh this one study that
cut two different amino acids uh said
you know there might be a benefit
that it's just not responsible
communication. So, um, so yeah, for
cancer there's a lot more uncertainty,
but at least what we can also say is
that there's research that's getting
further along that's looking at this and
seeing if there may be certain cancers
that may be susceptible to glycine
restriction and serarine restriction.
So, the combination. Okay. Now then I
revisited the topic because then I was
curious and I asked myself well is it
the glycine restriction or is it the
serene restriction that's causing or is
it both and I found some other studies
that were preclinical so we're not
talking about clinical research anymore
where they applied a dual restriction to
animals as well as to cells. And what
they found is that when they fed the
cancer cells
or when they restricted both serereine
and glycine, they were able to repeat
the experiment. What we saw with the
clinical data that uh cancer had more
difficulty
uh growing significantly greater uh
difficulty growing and would die more
and was just generally more stressed.
Then they did additional experiments
where they separated the two, right?
Where they only restricted serarine or
they only restricted glycine. And when
they restricted glycine,
there was no
reduction in cancer.
But when they rest restricted searing,
there was a reduction in cancer. So now
this tells us or at least it gives us
some clues that the effect is not driven
through glycine. It's driven through
serarine. It's the serarine restriction
that's most likely causing all these
effects that I just want to pause here.
It still doesn't mean that we should now
restrict serereine. We are talking about
preclinical. We're talking about less
than preclinical. We're talking about
cell studies. But it's teasing out the
mechanisms of how this works. Then there
was a specific study that did all these
tracing experiments where they literally
tag molecules of glycine and tag
molecules of serereine and they watch
not like by eye but they measure through
many different experiments what happens
where these tag serarine molecules and
glycine molecules end up in cancer cells
in a variety of different cancer cells.
And they showed that
there
if you restricted
searing or if you increased glycine. So
you increase glycine, not restrict but
increase glycine
is that there's a pool of glycine that
builds up within the cells that reverses
a particular biochemical process. So I'm
going to break that down.
Typically what would happen is searing
inside your cancer cell but also inside
your regular cells would convert
serereine to glycine. Okay? So that's
all you need to know. Searing gets
converted to glycine. In that conversion
process there is a loss or a a
production we'll call it a loss of a
carbon atom. So that car carbon atom
will
then go down a different pathway. So,
we've got serarine to glycine
and the the conversion from serarine to
glycine means that a carbon is removed
off of the searing molecule.
And as a result,
that carbon molecule goes down a
different pathway which ultimately
results in greater production of nucleic
acids. What are nucleic acids? Nucleic
acids are involved in the production of
DNA. So in the building blocks for DNA.
So obviously if you have a dividing cell
that needs to replicate all of its DNA,
then those carbons are incredibly
important, right? You're getting more of
these carbons shuttling off into this
system that then you know gets used for
DNA synthesis
and then therefore you get more cancer
cells. So the cancer cells get to grow.
So if you restrict serarine, well
obviously then you don't have any
conversion to glycine because well
there's no serarine. Okay? So none of
those carbons are going across because
they just don't exist. But on the other
hand, if you up glycine
then the pool of serene is smaller than
the pool of glycine in that scenario. So
now the reaction goes in the reverse. So
now instead of losing a carbon down this
pathway, you are taking carbons from
that pathway and putting it onto glycine
to create serarine.
So what does that do? Well, now you're
instead of adding things to it's like
it's like instead of adding things to a
house that you're building, you're now
taking different elements from that
house every time that you need something
and putting it somewhere else. So, is
the house being built or is it being
destroyed or is it being broken down?
Obviously, it's being broken down. And
that's the same with the cancer cell.
So, now the cancer cell no longer has
this reservoir or this pipeline, I
should say, of carbon. Okay, I had to
pause there for a second because a trash
truck just went by and made a whole
ruckus. So, hopefully I didn't lose my
train of thought too much. But
essentially, as I was saying, hopefully
I was saying that you have this carbon
that no longer then um gets sent down
this pipeline and ultimately you get
this uh stopping or slowing of the
cancer growth because the cancer cell no
longer can rely on those carbons to go
down and produce these nucleic acids to
produce these DNA um these DNA pieces
that are put together.
So that's the idea of the searing
restriction or the potentially the
increase in glycine which is definitely
in pre-clinical models as well. So we
don't have clinical data on that aspect.
So based on early data cell work some in
vivo work so in animals uh we have
evidence that the real culprit is
searing restriction. that is the one
that's going to be beneficial and not
the glycine restriction and maybe we'll
get that in uh clinical trials in in the
future but as it stands that's where we
are. Um, is this actionable? Like I know
this this is always really tricky
because people are often in
uh stressful situations where they have
to deal with cancer and whatnot. And
I I can't give you advice. Like I it's
just it's one I'm not your physician.
Like I I simply cannot and I refuse to
tell people, oh yes, definitely do this
and definitely do that and then do this
based on exactly what I was just railing
against before about, you know, these
like early signs of data and then I'm
not distinguishing what is rock solid
evidence we have and what is kind of
like ah we're not sure or we're early or
we're we don't have any real clue what
we're talking about in this category.
Like, so
sometimes people reach out and be like,
"Hey, I have leukemia or I have uh skin
cancer, I have melanoma, or I have like
whatever type of cancer." And I just
can't like I I always respond the same
way. I I can't tell you what exactly you
should do. It's it's not ethical for me.
And it's uh again, I'm not your
physician, so I don't know all the
details of your
special circumstance and whatnot. And
all I'm going to ethically tell you is
that we're very early in the research.
We at least have one cl like a little
bit of clinical evidence, which is
great. Um, and if you wanted to do it, I
mean, that's on you. That's, you know,
your choice that you need to discuss
with your physician. I know everybody,
there's a lot of people that sc my
physician, he they don't know, you know,
what they're talking about or and like
it sucks. like if you have a a bad
uh relationship with your physician, uh
I can't, you know, again, it's out of my
out of my wheelhouse. Um but if anybody
ever wants to get more experimental,
it's your body. Uh but you my only
advice ever is to at least consult with
a physician that actually knows your
circumstance. So is any of the stuff
that I just went over actionable? No.
Because at the very top we have a phase
one clinical trial. No one
would base huge like yes we have
definitive evidence based on a one a
single phase one clinical trial which by
the way also still had some people
progress in their cancer. The majority
didn't and a lot of people had
regression but some people still had
progression. So there's a lot of
uncertainty still. So anyway, I I'll get
off my soap box, but let's go over some
uh comments here related to the topic.
And the takeaway here is that glycine is
probably not the issue. Okay, so if
you're supplementing with glycine, my
estimation based on early data and with
no data on specific cancers, that's a
big caveat there, that glycine
supplementation is unlikely to be the
issue.
Okay, so Hawk Driver said, "I'm down to
celery and lemons. Everything else seems
destined to kill us." And it does feel
that way, right? Uh yeah, it it does
feel that way. You get told on social
media by health influencers, myself
included, that
uh you should
consume more glycine because, you know,
it'll
turn your gray hair back to their normal
color. you take glycine and your immune
system will be supercharged and like all
this stuff, right? You you just get told
all kinds of different things. And I'm
not even necessarily saying that some of
those videos aren't correct. Like some
of them can be right. They can be
focused on uh evidence. They present
that evidence and it's all it's all
above board. Um, I think the I think
it's the fault of both sides, honestly.
And I've been saying this for a long
time now and I'll probably continue to
say it for the rest of my life that on
one side the health influencers myself
included have to constantly be working
on how we communicate and how how do we
communicate ethically? How do we
communicate correctly while still and I
will like in defense I will say like if
your livelihood is on social media and
uh science or just communication health
communication doesn't even necessarily
have to be science communication
um
just giving information just like all
the information right at the get-go like
right at the beginning people really
complain about that like oh well why did
I have to watch an 8 minute video to to
understand this and it's like well for
me there's two reasons one is what I'm
talking about we make no money so we
just go extinct so all the benefits from
like having health influence and and
stuff just goes extinct if we don't have
a story that we can tell and the other
aspect is like honestly I don't I don't
like people that don't that aren't
curious that that don't want to
understand how these things work, aren't
asking questions, and if if you're the
type of person that just wants the
answer and then like I'm just thanks,
see you. I I
you and I are not the same type of
person. I just don't like that. I don't
want to be I don't want to foster
content that's just
here's the answer. Just believe me
because I have a PhD. Just believe me
because I I flashed a study. Look at
this study. And meanwhile, I'm not
demonstrating to you, hey, look, I read
this. I analyzed it. I I know what I'm
doing. Here are the statistics.
Understand some. I'm not saying like the
whole thing because I realize that that
can be a bridge too far. That can be a
little too far where it it gets too into
the weeds. But, you know, still it
should be on me to present to you and to
say, look, this is what the evidence
shows. This is what the evidence doesn't
show because if I give you a quick
answer and you run with it, that's the
problem. That's where we end up with I'm
down to celery and lemons. Everything
else seems destined to kill us because
now I'm not doing like you're not doing
your due diligence of like having a bit
of patience and understanding the
context around what we're talking about.
So let's return to this glycine
scenario, right?
The glycine scenario is like okay it can
be beneficial let's say against insulin
resistance like mild insulin resistance
or it can be uh beneficial in glyac
right for uh the combination of glycine
plus an acetylcysteine and it can
improve uh muscle function or
mitochondrial dysfunction or whatever
like just whatever just it can be a
number of different things
but let's say there was this study that
also showed that glycine is a negative
if you have melanoma. Very specifically,
let's just say, and I'm not stating this
as is as if there is a study to be
clear, but let's say there is a study
that says glycine fed to people that
with melanoma made melanoma grow more
quickly. Okay. So, does that now mean
does that translate that glycine is now
something to be avoided by everyone? No.
Right? No. No one in their right mind
would actually say, "Oh, well now uh I
can't take glycine." It's like that's
that's not how this works. That's not
how nuance works. That's not how an
educated person thinks. Like an educated
person thinks, okay, check one. Do I
have melanoma?
Answer, no. Therefore, does not apply to
me.
That's I mean, that's how you typically
think about things. So like, and I see
this so often, people just cross off an
entire nutrient or an entire food group
or an entire exercise or whatever
because a single study showed that there
is a negative for a very specific group
of people and they don't fit any of
those criteria, but they just cross it
off. And then and then we get these
complaints of like, well, one day they
say this and then the next day they say
that and then the other day it's like I
don't know how many times in my videos
that I've pulled together like 10
different studies
and eight of them say kind of something
in the same realm and then two of the
studies disagree. And it's like if you
were to actually read all those studies,
you would understand, oh, maybe those
two studies were in particular like they
they were in let's say women and the
eight other studies were in men. Okay,
so maybe that's the defining feature of
maybe this is uh a negative for women
and it may be a benefit for men. Wow,
look at that. We have nuance now. We
have some understanding of it. It
affects people differently and you have
to understand your circumstance. Does
that actually apply to you? Do you fit
the bill here? And if you don't, then
don't worry about it. Don't this doesn't
apply to you. Uh don't cross it off just
because there's a study or or a few
studies or whatever it might be. Now, on
the other side, the the health
influencer has to do a good job of
explaining that, hey, this was an
overweight people. this was in people
that were in their 60s. Uh the there was
other studies in people that were in
their 30s and it had no effect or
whatever it might be. Like that's where
the health influencer, the communicator
has to be better. And this is something
I'm constantly working on to give all
the information that's pertinent that
needs to be said so that a person can
make that that categorization that that
that you know like oh do I fit in this
bucket or not as opposed to just saying
moringa powder is the best thing in the
world. You put it in a coffee and your
visceral fat gets cut by a,000%. Not
possible, but by a,000%, you turn into a
you turn into Brad Pit and like all
these different things. It's just like
the best thing ever. And then the next
video, uh, glycine supplementation,
that's the thing that's going to cure
your insomnia and like all these
different things. And then people try it
and then it's like, okay, maybe it
worked, maybe it didn't. There's just so
much to be said. So
that's where like picking the the people
that are going to be more nuanced and
actually have those discussions uh is
critically important and for the viewer
for that person to really sit and think
and like okay does this apply to me in
this situation? Um and generally the
answer is no, right? Okay. Anyway,
party DM party DM me. I'm pretty sure
it's party DM. I swear every time I
start something for supposed health
benefits, YouTube pops up a video
showing how detrimental it is. What the
hell? Okay, so I'm not going to repeat
it, but same story again, just context.
Following people that will actually sit
down and explain, you know, okay, maybe
it might affect these people. It's
probably not going to affect these
people. So, you're probably okay. Uh,
and at the same time, the viewer having
the patience to sit there and be like,
"Okay, I'm going to sit down for this
10-minute video and watch it and a help
this this content creator continue to be
ethical and all that, you know, do the
right thing, which they should be doing
regardless.
And at the same time also I'm going to
learn I'm going to put it upon myself to
learn this context and understand
everything that needs to be said uh so
that I can make those distinctions so
I'm not in this like what the hell kind
of scenario.
Sabrina
said I'm truly confused. I thought
glycine was an anti-cancer and
anti-aging and antioxidant. It seems
that every other week that we get
conflicting information. I feel that
anything is cancerinducing at this
point. I think the best way to live is
just to enjoy life and to avoid any
obvious toxins such as tobacco, alcohol,
and drugs, including sugar, and leave it
to the man upstairs. The more I educate
quote unquote myself, the more I feel
that I have no idea what's going on.
Okay, this is kind of in the same vein,
right? But in addition to that, I agree
with Sabrina that you know just focusing
the the big levers, the huge levers
uh to to pull on are definitely Yeah.
just enjoy life. Avoid
obvious things like tobacco, alcohol.
It's not like there's going to be a
study that's going to come out and say
say like, "Hey, tobacco, we were wrong
about tobacco. Tobacco is actually uh
really good for you. It's absolutely
fantastic for you." Nobody's going to
say that. Like there's certain things
that are really it wouldn't shock me if
we had a study that showed that a
particular group of people that have
this particular gene expressed may not
experience the negative effects of
tobacco. Could that happen? Yes. But
does that then translate to everybody,
hey, tobacco is no longer an issue? No,
you're not going to see that. So, yes,
to Sabrina's point, like the big levers,
exercise, nutrition, making sure you
avoid tobacco, um, you know, smoking,
vaping, uh, alcohol, drugs. Of course, I
don't know if I'd necessarily include
sugar. Like, people kind of talk about
sugar like it's like some specific thing
that's not really a nutrient when in
reality it gets broken down inside your
body. The exact same. If it comes from
white bread, if it comes from wheat, if
it comes from uh fruity loops, whatever
like cereal, whatever it is, um
ultimately gets broken down into glucose
and that's what gets absorbed into your
bloodstream. So,
it's a whole another conversation and
there's certainly some nuances there to
also be had. Would I put that on the
same category as like actual drugs like
I don't know heroin or something? No.
No. Not not even close. And in fact, you
can check out I did one on fructose uh
centerfuge episode fructose and Dr.
Listik who's huge against fructose and
you know there's some some reasoning for
that. Um but so I'd encourage that you
check that out. But yeah, I mean these
comments again like they're they're
among my top comments, you know, and so
this this sentiment is continuous.
People really feel strongly that,
you know, health influencers saying one
thing and then they're saying something
completely different the next day, the
next week, whatever. I I totally get
that. I and I'm I'm not I'm not uh
immune. I I definitely understand that
and I get frustrated. Why do you think I
started the centerfuge? Like it's so
much work. But I'm I feel so
passionately that people are just
miscommunicating.
And I'll even say it as far as
malcommunicating.
The distinction in my head is
miscommunication could be like, you
know, they don't know any better. I'll
be honest. I really think I'm not going
to name any names, but I really I get
the impression that some health
influencers are actually like they don't
care if they hurt people
because it's not direct. It's just oh,
I'm just providing information. Uh but
like the the gross negligence in certain
scenarios and especially when people get
get called out and said, "Hey, uh you
missed this thing and it's like a huge
thing or you missed like all these
different factors or the study that you
that you were talking about didn't
conclude any of what you just said." Uh,
I mean that kind of stuff like if you I
understand people have like sometimes
they have such big platforms like I miss
a lot and that's why I've got like a
critique page so people can click on the
link and send me a direct critique.
People abuse that all the time. But
aside from that, I have received
critiques and I take great pride in the
fact that I will read that comment
especially if it comes from a researcher
or a physician or or but it can be
anyone, right? As long as they provide
proof like evidence that I got something
wrong or whatever. I remember once
I royally messed up on a metaanalysis
and I've learned a lot uh since then,
but there was this metaanalysis
researcher researcher that actually
conducted metaanalysis and she really
laid into me. I could tell she was just
really frustrated
uh with with just like bad information
being put out there. Um, it wasn't like,
you know, I was misleading the public or
anything like that, but just like there
was a few statistical things that I was
explaining in certain ways that she
didn't agree with. And she was more of
an expert on the topic than I was. So
she sent me this long thing and at the
end like she was like I don't even know
if you're going to read this
which like I again I understood like it
was her feel the thing that she was
really passionate about and she wanted
she was just like letting me know and I
I'm glad that she did. I'm really glad
that she did because I reached out to
her the next day. I was like hey do you
mind if we hop on a on a video call? Um,
and she ended up like apologizing for
like being so aggressive towards me and
everything. And we had a lovely
conversation and she taught like she she
taught me and I and I said like, "Hey,
in the future in the future uh maybe we
can have more of these conversation. I'd
be happy to pay for your time." And
we've had like we've had other
conversations just like spoken in
general just on on video chat and email
and whatnot. And it's Yeah. I mean, and
I I took I took the video down. I posted
a uh like a a notice, like an amendment
um for whatever needed to be fixed. And
then I I contacted her about like a few
different resources that I could read uh
to learn more about the topic. So, this
was like on um this was on a very
particular like statistical modeling in
in meta analysis. And she was really
kind. She sent me a few resources and I
ended up buying a book and honestly it's
dense. I've gotten about like 3/4 of the
way through it and I'm probably going to
have to go through it again. But it's a
wonderful resource. Anyway, the the
short story of this is that it's
incredibly important for me to get
things right. And if I get things wrong
so that I can get things right, then I'm
willing to do that. That is perfectly
fine. and I'm not above uh like my pride
isn't going to jump over the potential
that I could be harming other people.
That that that re that that will never
happen. Um and
you know since then because again I'm
I'm growing and I'm trying to improve.
I've hired statisticians before to check
over some of my work. Not you know not
every video but like for some of the
things that I'm not quite sure on. Uh
and now we've got AI. I know that AI can
have its issues and of course I fact
check that information too. Um but it's
just important. So when I see some
health influencers
just post information and again just to
repeat I understand some people have
millions of subscribers so they're not
going to get every email but when you
have a ground swell of people that are
like hey this person screwed up and
here's the evidence and like they they
clearly didn't read the study or
whatever whatever it might be. It could
be anything. um and that person doesn't,
you know, address the issue.
I'm not talking about like, hey, I don't
like the way this person talks or
whatever. I'm talking about scientific
evidence, like they're they're just not
addressing data. They they got a lot of
things wrong. All that stuff. That is
stuff that you should address. If you're
a science communicator, that is
something that you need to take down
videos. You need to send, you know, post
amendments. And that's why under my
videos sometimes I'll post uh minor
amendments if I get something wrong. I
think recently I did one on uh
polyunsaturated fats being converted. So
I I accidentally had an image of a
saturated fat being converted to an
omega-3.
And I do check my comments uh in the
first like hour or so of posting. I try
to engage as much as I can. And somebody
pointed that out and said, "Hey, you
messed this up," which I'm glad. So, I
checked and sure enough, I had a
saturated fat being converted to, I
think, an omega-3. And that can't
happen. That doesn't happen in the human
body. What happens is you have
unsaturated fats that are elongated into
omega-3s. So, I posted an amendment and
I added it to my articles and all that
stuff. So, again, the the point here is
that there's a lot of health
influencers. They're putting out just
trash information. And honestly, I think
some of them know that it's trash
information and they just don't care.
So, when I get comments
like the ones that I just did that I
just pointed out,
it's not people saying like, "Hey, uh,
so, you know, I heard glycine is good
for this." It's like they're just
expressing their frustration that
there's so much information out there
that one day they say this, one day they
say that. I'm with you. Like I'm on I'm
on the same page. Uh and I think that
the issue is two-sided. The health
influencers and some viewers. So some
health influencers and some viewers. Uh
not everyone obviously. Um so yeah.
Anyway, I I'll move on. All right. The
next topic that I wanted to get into is
to get into my favorite anti-aging hack.
And this anti-aging hack is an
incredibly simple one. It is
sunscreen, which I know isn't all that
exciting, but it is important at least
uh from an aging perspective and
certainly you could argue from a
uh cancer perspective or at least skin
cancer perspective. So, I released this
analysis where I I just did this not
because this is some miraculous
discovery or anything like that.
Certainly not. But I did want to cover
this simply because I am a pretty big
sunscreen fanatic
and
I was just curious as to what kind of
impact wearing sunscreen on a daily
basis like right now I'm wearing
sunscreen of course certainly when I'm
outdoors but uh I even wear it indoors
what kind of impact that sunscreen would
have on aging metrics. So, I found a
number of different studies on the topic
and admittedly
those studies are not very high quality,
at least uh some of them. But all of
them point the same direction and and
probably isn't too much of a shock uh to
know that sunscreen can significantly
slow and in one study actually
completely stop uh visible signs of
aging. And I've been a pretty big fan of
sunscreen since I was about 28. And I am
now closer to 40 than I am to 30. And I
think, at least from my estimation, I
think that it's it's helped. Uh I'm not
saying that it stops skin aging or
anything of that nature, but I think
that uh it definitely has a significant
impact. And I don't think that it's
something that we should overlook.
uh even though it may not be very sexy,
right? It's not like taking some super
supplement or something like that like
NAD boosters or anything like that uh
that's suddenly going to rejuvenate your
cells back to their 18-year-old
versions. Um but
it if you especially if you jump on it
early in life, I think you can have a
really substantial impact on uh the way
you look at least. Certainly that
doesn't necessarily speak to your liver
health and your heart health and all
these different other aspects and in
that regard you probably have to do
other things obviously exercise being
one of them and there's even evidence
and I've covered this before that
exercise can be helped or sorry that
skin can be helped through exercise as
well as in if you exercise your skin
tends to be uh better for it as well.
So, do I think that sunscreen will stop
aging like that one study showed?
There's this one study that uh compared
uh I think like infrequent to no
sunscreen use versus a group that was
told to uh use sunscreen I think every
single day. And they showed that the
group that used sunscreen every day for
four and a half years, something like
that, 5 years, uh was able to completely
stop their aging, skin aging, and that
was determined by uh I believe blinded
dermatologists.
Now, does that actually mean that these
people were completely like not aging
whatsoever? I don't think so. I think
what's probably happening is that it
slows it to such a degree that it seems
like uh these people haven't aged over
the last 5 years. But I think if they'd
used some more objective metrics like
actual like collagen levels or if they'd
done some sort of ultrasound or
different um echo
uh technologies to really figure out the
uh density of the collagen or the
different uh fibers that are within the
skin or the skin cells themselves, I'm
pro I'm pretty sure that they would have
discovered some sort of an effect as in
these people were still aging over time.
still not bad. I mean, if you're, you
know, 5 years isn't like a monumental
amount of time, but it's certainly
something. And I think it's pretty
impressive that you can just put
something on your skin and it can
protect you from uh UV radiation, which
is the primary method by which uh skin a
or I should say uh sunscreen helps
against uh skin aging. And of course in
my latter part of my analysis I went
over a few intervention trials looking
at uh skin cancer and showed that uh the
sunscreen can also reduce our risk of
skin cancer by a pretty substantial
amount. So all in all, definitely
something that uh I encourage people
that are that want to retain as much of
their skin youth as possible. Um, okay.
So, that brings me to kind of the
to another part of that analysis, which
I know that a lot of people are
skeptical of sunscreens because they are
endocrine disc disruptors and uh bunch
of other, you know, things that have
been said in the past. And I'll admit
that there are I did look at the studies
on that and um I'll admit that there are
not very many studies that have actually
specifically looked to check if
sunscreens are safe in uh the doses that
are applied.
Uh there's one study that looked at the
hormonal changes over some number of
months
and they did show that there was a
slight change in hormonal profile from
sunscreen use
I think in the first month and then
after followup so continuing to use
sunscreen but in followup you know two
three months later their hormones
returned back to uh before they were
using sunscreen.
So, how applicable any of that is, like
what difference is that going to make, I
don't know. Um, and I don't think it's
probably something that you need to
really worry about a whole lot.
Uh, the other aspect is, you know, I've
I looked at like sunscreen and mortality
there and other some like kind of major
metrics like what we discussed earlier
and there doesn't seem to be much of a
link. Um the
I will say that again there isn't like a
whole lot of literature if people are
under the impression that there's a ton
of literature that shows that where
we've applied sunscreen and then we've
measured cardiovascular health then
we've measured cancer then we've
measured all these different things.
We've measured I don't know like all
kinds of different niche conditions and
then determined oh it's all good to all
good to go. That's not how the
literature actually looks. um the
literature, you know, there's there's
quite a few studies on sunscreen, but
there just aren't enough to cover all of
our bases. Really, it's deemed safe
because of the ingredients are in such
small quantities that the governing
bodies just deemed them as highly
unlikely to have any sort of impact. And
that's because in terms of like blood
impact and organ impact and whatnot. And
the reason for that is just because
there has to be a certain threshold at
which you are
getting exposed to a particular uh
molecule. And when it comes to sunscreen
ingredients, the threshold we're well I
mean just like with many other things
like aspartame and sucralose and all
these other things um whatever I'm just
coming up with different molecules that
are deemed as like such small amounts of
it that uh it's assumed that there isn't
that much of an impact or any impact on
your organs in any sort of negative uh
way simply because uh you consuming such
a small amount by comparison to what's
deemed actually uh dangerous based off
of like animal studies and sort of some
of the biochemical studies. So
I don't and also even if you were to
have some small impact how much would
that translate over time that's another
aspect um you know if you have a
minuscule effect is that is that going
to outweigh the huge benefit that you
get to your skin aging but even more
importantly probably skin cancer. So,
you know, then there's certainly other
ways of going about it. Like there's
also physical types of sunscreen.
There's physical blocks and then there's
chemical blocks. I don't really care
that much about the distinction. Um, but
some people really do care and that's
perfectly fair. There are advantages and
disadvantages to both. Some of them are
just more cosmetic. Um,
and the I don't use really high SPF. I
use SPF 15 and SPF 30. SPF 15. Uh, when
it's not very sunny out, when there's
it's not like middle of summer, um,
middle of summer, I usually use SPF 30.
I use it on my skin, my neck, and I will
put it on my arms. I actually forgot to
do that right now. And you can see I'm
getting a lot of sun exposure at the
moment. Um, I'm not going to fret about
it, but I probably will uh get sunburnt
unless I move out of the way. So, you
know what? I'm going to move a little
bit back.
Ha. I've outsmarted the sun. Okay, so um
yeah, so that's that's where I kind of
land on this favorite anti-aging hack.
Again, we get so focused on the the
different consumables, and I'm not
saying that they don't have an impact,
but uh some of the stuff is so obvious,
right? Like just exercise or just uh
dial in your nutrition or even just
broad strokes. You know, if you're if
you're overweight and you're worried
about like NMN supplementation,
what are you doing? You should be
focused on uh getting weight under
control because that is going to have
mass mass much more like mass more
impact than uh like NMN supplementation
for example or whatever it might be. So,
and I think uh sunscreen is just one of
those, especially in summer, that is
just such a no-brainer. Um, and if you
want to go other routes, like if you
want to protect your skin through other
roots, like uh wearing uh more clothing,
like sunprotective clothing or whatever
it might be, then uh that's that's a way
to go. Now, one of the critiques, I
don't know if I've got some comments
here.
Oh, yeah. Okay. Okay. So, I'm going to
I'm going to cover one of the major
critiques that was presented to me uh
based on what I was talking about in
terms of sunscreen uh to be so just as a
final word, the way the sunscreen
protects us is from uh exttrinsic
versions of or extrinsic exttrinsic
factors of aging. Meaning that you have
something from outside of the body
that's affecting the body and then
causing aging. And same thing, same
exact route for cancer in this situation
because we're talking about UV radiation
and that's going to be important in just
a minute. So UV radiation has an impact
on our skin which ultimately breaks down
our skin and um or I shouldn't say the
skin itself. that has has an impact on
the DNA that's within our uh
keratinocytes
which are the skin cells and then they
don't function as well because they
they're constantly repairing this DNA
damage which ultimately can lead to of
course cancer but can also lead to uh
disregulation of the cells. Essentially,
the cells just don't uh connect with one
another because there's these different
kind of um think of them like anchoring
proteins where they anchor onto one
another like they're holding hands
almost and that can get disregulated so
that the cells are not as bound to one
another so you've got less of a skin
barrier integrity. Obviously, it can
affect the collagen fibers that go
through uh the
now I'm through the epidermis uh which
is a section of your skin which creates
the actual like lattice structure that
holds the skin up. So, there's a number
of different things and the the the
sunblock sunscreen can depending on
which one you're using essentially just
uh has it has the UV interact with it
instead of interacting with uh all those
different components that I just talked
about and there's many other factors.
Then there's intrinsic aging which is
something that we can't really avoid. um
it's just chronological age. You know,
as time passes, our cells are imperfect.
So, they're going to make replication
errors and all kinds of other things
which ultimately leads us to uh have
problems that we we try to avoid, right,
through supplementation, exercise,
nutrition, all that good stuff. and
potentially gene editing or gene
therapies in the future or gene whatever
or stem cells or all kinds of different
medical technologies for the future. But
uh those are things that are you know
they're not necessar I guess they can be
preventative but um generally it's it's
going to be extremely difficult to get
people to reverse their aging to that
degree because there's so many intrinsic
factors that happen in all kinds of
different organ systems that we have to
account for and uh that's just not
always possible.
So okay. So now let me uh so that's all
to say sunscreen specifically affects
exttrinsic aging. It has no real impact
on intrinsic aging. Okay. So let's go
into some comments.
So
Patrick said again these are the top
comments or among the top comments. Uh
Patrick was surprised that I was that I
had said in my analysis that I was uh
closer to 40 than I am uh to 30
and
mentioned that uh sunscreen was working
for me which I appreciate. Thank you
Patrick. The final Roman said which
sunscreen do you use? So like I said I
don't use very strong sunscreen SPF 15
SPF 30. I reapply often uh two, three
times a day, especially when I'm
outdoors. I appi apply uh pretty
regularly. I always wear sunscreen. I
know people will think that's kind of
crazy to be wearing sunscreen every
single day. I use it every single day.
It doesn't matter if I'm going outside
or in or staying in indoors. I wear it
all the time.
That's definitely why I'm as pale as I
am. Uh, and the type of sunscreen that I
use is Cetaphil. Um, it but I'm not like
it's it's not because Cedaphil is some
sort of specialty brand or anything like
that. Um, it's legitimately just because
it's cheap. It's I don't get it in my
eyes. Um, it just like just goes across
my my skin really well. And the other
Oh, yeah. There's a there is a
particular type of sunscreen ingredient
that I truly wish would get approved in
the United States. I think it's called
bimotisenol
and that has been is probably going to
be like a golden child of sunscreen
ingredients and for some reason I
shouldn't say some reason the FDA has
not approved any new sunscreen
ingredients in like 20 years um if not
more and bimatrizenol is one of those
that's approved in like the EU Australia
and all these other places uh that's
just not approved in in the US which is
unfortunate it because um apparently
it's better at blocking uh UVA and UVB
radiation. Um but on top of that, it
also doesn't uh leech into the blood,
which certain chemical sunscreens do
leech into the blood. Um and then you
can, you know, be pretty safe in
assuming that you're not going to have
any sort of consequences. I still don't
think that there are going to be any
consequences of um of those trace
amounts of sunscreen ingredient uh
leeching in, but I know a lot of people
are like, "Well, look, I mean, it
leeching into my blood is is already
scary enough," which is totally fair.
Like I, you know, I respect that. Um,
bimatrizenol, I hope I'm getting the the
ingredient correct, uh, is something
that I would just love to see actually
get approved and hopefully in the future
we will. And the moment that does,
whatever company uses that, I'm going to
uh switch over to to that. Um, but yeah,
SPF 15, I use Cedaphil, but I'm I'm
pretty uh ambivalent. I could I could go
either way to any one of the other
ingredients. I've tried a few others. I
just don't like the the feel of them on
my skin.
Okay, then the critique. Now, this comes
from uh Lenny. So, Lenny, you should
take a look at the UK bioank study. This
is an AI overview when asked about it
and sun exposure. Okay. So UK bioank
studies uh study particularly analyses
of over 370,000 to 400,000 participants
by the University of Edinburgh suggest
that higher ultraviolet exposure from
sun or sunbeds is associated with lower
allc cause cardiovascular and cancer
mortality.
These findings indicate that in low
sunlight, high alitude regions, the
cardiovascular benefits of sun exposure
likely outweigh risks for white
populations potentially increasing
lifespan. Ooh, well then I better get
more sun exposure and just forget about
the sunscreen.
Yeah. So, that's that's a good AI
overview of what the study indicates,
but that doesn't mean that the study is
correct.
And
it seems weird to say that uh but I was
intrigued. So I know that MedCram had
released a a video about this particular
study, this UK bioank study which has
not been published yet, but it's in
preprint. So it is accessible to the
public. And I I decided to look at that.
And uh
it's
it's not as
great of a study as people are making it
out to be. And I I don't necessarily
fault I don't fault the researchers. Uh
I don't think the researchers did
anything wrong.
I think that just UV studies in general
or sun studies in general are much more
difficult to control than
people think.
So, with nutrition, there's a lot like
there's certainly issues in nutrition um
as well when you're talking about
long-term studies, but there have been
some really good long-term studies in
nutrition
because of how rigorous they've been
about controlling, I should say more so
measuring different factors.
um in UV exposure
studies. I looked at this study and what
they did is like this AI overview said
yes it was like 400,000 people and they
categorized them into low, medium and
high exposure to UV so ultraviolet
radiation
which comes from the sun and in this
case from the sun and so what they
showed and it's true that that AI
overview says what's correct so it
showed that those with the higher
UV exposure or sun exposure
had
and they were more specific about UV but
so that's going to be one of the
sticking points they said more UV
exposure was linked to reduced mortality
if that's all cause mortality
cardiovascular mortality and even cancer
mortality though they did uh show a
slight increase in skin cancer mortality
which so but other types of cancers were
improved prod at least associatively.
Now, I had a number of problems with
this study. Uh I'm not going to
regurgitate everything that I went over
in my analysis. I'll link that for you.
But one of the issues is one of the big
issues is that they kept referencing
everything to UV, as in UV was
associating with these things. And
that's technically correct. But can we
then jump to UV being the cause of these
things? And I'm not talking about just
simple correlation is not causation
because there are many epidemiological
studies that are really well done as in
you know they they they measure a bunch
of different factors that could uh be
the real reason for the results that we
see. And
I've I've been a big fan of those
studies. So I can't, you know, double
back and suddenly be like, oh, you know,
it's correlation, so therefore it's not,
you know, causitive. Um, because that's
just not fair.
However,
when you're talking about UV radiation
in that study, as from what I read and I
read the whole thing, but you know,
maybe I missed it mentioned once, they
never mention red light or
uh near infrared light or infrared light
or whatever you want to call it. Um, and
yet like red light is one of the major
components of sunlight and we have many
studies at this point showing that other
forms of light like red light have
positive effects on the body.
And yet we don't have nearly the same
evidence indicating that UV
ultraviolet light is
causing you know positive effects. There
are a few studies that show improvements
in like blood pressure and things of
that nature, but there's also tons of
studies that directly show that UV is
extremely harmful. Um, especially at
high doses, can cause cancer, cause lead
to death. Um, and I showed some in my
analysis, I showed some direct like
pre-clinical evidence indicating that,
you know, when you expose certain
animals or life forms to UV,
uh, they die very quickly. um when
they're highly exposed to UV. Now, of
course, it could be dose, you know, dose
makes the poison and all that good
stuff, but what we don't have is the
same thing as far as I'm aware in like
red light. So, this whole study was
based on UV associated with reduced
mortality. Okay. So, and this AI
overview actually makes a mistake. It
says uh suggest that higher ultraviolet
exposure from sun or sunbeds. Okay. So,
one, the researchers did not specify
what sunlamp was. They did mention a
sunlamp or I'm sorry, salarium, which I
I postulate I guessed.
Okay, maybe maybe it is uh what they're
talking about is a tanning bed. And but
it could be if you look up the
definition for salarium, it could be a
um a sun room, it can be a tanning bed,
and it can be a sunlamp.
So which is it? And they didn't define
it. So I just went ahead with the
assumption that it was tanning beds. And
this AI thing seems to think that that's
also what uh what it was. And so what I
did is I found some other studies that
looked at tanning beds and uh sun
exposure. And then we'll be able to
tease out the difference between is it
sun exposure or is it the the UV itself?
Because tanning beds largely provide
only UV radiation. They do not provide
much if any red light. I'm just focusing
on red light. But
the sun obviously exposes us to more
than just UV. It exposes us to red
light. So now we'll be able to
distinguish between is it the UV or is
it something else in the sun.
And lo and behold,
the study that looked at both showed
that those with the tanning bed that
were using the tanning beds a lot
actually had increased risk of mortality
and increased cancer risk. However,
those that were exposed to the sun had
reduced risk of mortality. So that's
exactly in line with that UK bio bank in
the sunlight exposure, but it is not the
same in terms of UV exposure. So the UK
bioank study in my opinion, my humble
opinion
is conflating UV radiation with red
light. I think red light is the actual
exposure, the actual mediator of the
benefit and UV is just being tracked. So
UV is the one that we're actually
tracking and it's not the UV that's
actually causing the benefits. So that
leads me back to sunscreen because then
I was curious, does sunscreen block out
red light? And the answer is no. So, you
could safely take sunscreen or use
sunscreen, block out what I deem the the
harmful aspect of sunlight, and still be
outside and exposed to and get the
benefits of
the positives of sunlight, which is red
light and infrared light and etc. So,
that's my take and I certainly had more
critiques of the study uh like how they
measured sun exposure and a bunch of
other things. Uh but I will leave that
for my full analysis um which I will
link for you. Anyway, that's where I
stand with that. If you're watching the
video version of this podcast, you're
going to see the frame continuously
change as I continue to try to escape
the sun. I promise I'm not a sun phobe.
I'm uh just getting rather warm, so I'm
trying to stay in the shade. Um I
promise I'm not a vampire.
Okay, let's get into lithium. So
last year I covered a nature study that
looked at and brought a lot of promise
to the idea that lithium could be a
molecule that could affect or yeah a
molecule that could affect Alzheimer's
disease in a pretty significantly
positive way. That study looked at
humans in a cross-sectional way as in
they uh looked at human brains
of people with Alzheimer's and then
determined that their lithium levels
were quite low. So then they did some
pre-clinical work so all in animals and
had an Alzheimer's model and then they
applied lithium to that Alzheimer's
model to see if it might have some sort
of benefit. Uh the answer was yes. It
showed significant benefit. So of course
you know knowing me hopefully at this
point uh you know that I wasn't just
going to leave it at that if there was
evidence in humans. And lo and behold I
did find a few studies that showed that
you know clinical studies showing hey
look uh lithium
does benefit the brain and helps fight
Alzheimer's disease.
So
that was great news. So then I released
this analysis and then uh showing that
you know lithium may be a future avenue
by which we can uh combat and reverse uh
signs of Alzheimer's disease. Okay, fair
enough. Now a physionic insider which I
pay a lot more attention to the
insiders. I'm very uh involved there.
Um, so I check in every day and a
physionic insider sent me or made me
aware that there was a new lithium meta
analysis.
That metaanalysis
indicated or put together all of the
studies on lithium and indicated that
there was no benefit.
And beyond that, they even showed that
one of the studies that I had used in my
analysis last year
uh was a high risk of bias study as in
they didn't uh use the appropriate uh
controls or not all of the appropriate
controls. Okay, so that certainly perked
my interest. Piqued my interest. Perked
my piqued my interest. And
uh again I I said this at the you know
another point in the podcast. I don't
care about being wrong as long as I end
up right. And what I mean by that is
that I want to get the right information
out. So if I have to be wrong uh to do
that then so be it. That's fine by me.
Um you know obviously I want to do a
good job. So I don't want to
continuously you know every analysis I
get everything wrong. That would that
would that would be a bit that would be
a gut punch because that'd be like,
okay, you need to really reconsider
things. But um so anyway, I looked at
this uh meta analysis to see if I had
gotten something wrong and I was wholly
unimpressed by the analysis uh for
multiple reasons. Again, I'm not going
to go through every detail. Uh they did
bring up some good points like this uh
this one study that was pretty you know
high risk of bias and that was the study
that showed the greatest benefit of
lithium. So obviously it's going to lead
to some like oh wow okay maybe
um maybe we got this wrong. Uh so
instead of recently what I've been doing
with meta analyses and I it takes a lot
of work but I've been opening up every
study that they include in the meta
analysis. If it's a meta analysis of
like 30 studies, I use a random sample
and I try to get the majority of the
studies. So, I'll pick like 16 studies
out of 30 at a random with a random
number generator and I'll open up those
16 studies and uh you know do a deeper
analysis on those 16 studies. But
anyway, this study was I think like six
studies or eight studies something like
that. It was seven, I don't know,
somewhere in that realm. Not like a huge
analysis or anything. So, I was able to
look at all of them or all the ones that
I could get my hands on, which was most
of the studies.
And
yeah, when I opened up these uh these
studies, I was
not blown away by how the meta analysis
was conducted.
And one of the primary reasons is
because
they included certain studies and then
for some reason they either didn't find
them or for whatever reason they failed
to include other studies that I ended up
discovering existed. And these studies
actually show a benefit of lithium. So
if you have an analysis that's on the
cusp of identifying a benefit of lithium
but it doesn't it the end result is
there is no benefit of lithium
supplementation against Alzheimer's
but you fail to include a few studies
that do show a benefit of lithium
then to me that translates to well if
you had included those studies as well
then you probably would have found an
effect
and so that's where I ended up landing.
I just didn't think that the meta
analysis was that convincing and I I
they they missed some studies. They by
their inclusion and exclusion criteria,
those studies met the inclusion criteria
and they did not meet the exclusion
criteria. So therefore, they should have
been included and for some reason they
weren't. I'm not saying it's for
nefarious reasons. I'm just saying that
it just wasn't included. Okay. So that
being the case, uh I did have a slightly
more muted uh interpretation because I I
do think there's a lot of uncertainty
when it comes to lithium. Not that there
because there are some studies that show
that there's no effect. And one of the
gripes that I had with this analysis is
that they included studies that lasted
eight weeks or 12 weeks and those
studies almost un I think universally
showed no effect of lithium. But again,
like you're applying
eight weeks of a treatment or 12 weeks
of a treatment to a disease that lasts
uh that that starts to appear like a
decade earlier and you expect it to just
have an effect. Uh I think that's
unreasonable. Um so to include two
studies or three studies that were such
short duration
I think is an unfair way to go about uh
the analysis. And I think if I think
they should have done their exclusion
criteria to to exclude studies that were
you know less than let's say 6 months.
But anyway when you exclude those
studies and you just focus on the longer
term studies there are most of those
studies showed an effect of lithium. It
wasn't like massive but there was an
effect of lithium. In addition there was
like one or two studies clearly it was
more than seven studies in the overall
analysis. Maybe it was like 11. But
there were a few long-term studies that
also showed there was no effect of
lithium. So now we've got a mixture of
evidence. I still lean in the direction
of favoring lithium, but I think that us
going wholeheartedly with lithium and
saying, "Oh, there's undeniable proof,"
I think is a little premature. Um,
actually, I would say it's quite
premature.
So that's what I in essentially
concluded in my reanalysis of lithium
that look, I'm still in favor, but you
know, we we definitely need more clarity
and there's definitely some things that
we're missing here and I'd like to see
some better research that's been that's
going to be done. And then when I
reported the dose of lithium that was
used, which is one area where I did
change my mind, um because the initial
dose that I had seen in some of the
clinical trials was micro uh microgram
doses. So we're talking about 300
micrograms,
which was shown to be effective.
So trace doses
all the way up to I think like 300 or
600 mg of lithium uh lithium salt. So,
elemental lithium at 300 micrograms and
then up to like 600 mg of uh lithium
salt. So, lithium salt being like carb
lithium carbonate, lithium sulfate,
lithium gluconate.
And that's where I
ended the analysis. Okay. And that's
where people uh some people jump down my
throat.
So, I'm going to read some of the
comments and then uh I will continue
discussing this a bit a bit more. So,
the comments were TRLD said this. So, I
need to stop eating my spent batteries.
Good one. TRLD, uh which is also kind of
a funny uh uh name for username for for
YouTube. Um, well, you probably
shouldn't have been consuming spent
batteries in the first place, but I I
see your point. Ed said this. I think
you screwed up on this post, Nick. Uh,
are you saying that this study in nature
was not a clinical trial? Please amplify
as you are confusing many of us. Okay,
so Ed is talking about this nature study
that I initially covered, right? And as
you heard me discuss,
I said that there was some
cross-sectional data in humans and then
the rest of it was all uh in
animals, pre-clinical uh models using
lithium. So, and never in my initial
analysis did I ever claim that this was
a clinical trial. Never said that. I
covered some clinical trials, but none
of them were the nature paper. And the
nature paper is the one that created all
this buzz. So the conclusion that you
know the nature paper is somehow a
clinical trial I don't know how people
got to that conclusion um because I have
never uttered those words in my life. So
for clarity the big nature paper that's
that came out last year was in no way
shape or form a clinical trial. It was
all preclinical data. Okay? So I just
want to make that clear.
Now, the next comment, I have to zoom in
here real quick. I I got some I got some
heated push back. Uh, Robert Williams
said,
"This post is very annoying. You are
rolling back support for lithium, yet
you say there are benefits, but we don't
know."
Yet you say there are benefits, but we
don't know what lithium salt this
metaanalysis includes.
Okay, I I'll respond in just a bit. It
was only micro doses of lithium oritate
that had the pre the previously proposed
benefits. You also mentioned that the
range of dosing varies widely from micro
to 300 mg. Such wide ranges of dosing
can't be combined for a sensible
analysis. I see no reason to disregard
the positive findings of the Harvard
study. To be clear, that's the Nature
study that I've been talking about.
People are fighting for their lives,
hanging in on to any positive studies
and don't need to be hit with confusing
studies that make no sense. I'm a big
fan of yours, but this
Okay, so let me break this down, Robert.
Uh, first off, thank you. I appreciate
it. I'm always appreciative of anybody
who who watches my content, uh, cares
about anything that I have to say on
anything. Uh, so I do appreciate it. Um,
now I'd like to just address some of
these and I I did comment uh under
Robert's uh post
because I there are a few errors in this
comment. Um
so for one we do know
the salts used in the meta analysis and
that's actually very specifically why I
mentioned only those salts uh in my
analysis. So I said 300 micrograms to I
guess 300 milligrams. I thought it was
600 milligrams. You can go 300
milligrams of these uh salts. And the
salts that were used were exactly the
three that I mentioned. Carbonate, uh,
sulfate and gluconate.
And
so that for sure. Then uh, Robert says
he also mentioned that range of dosing
varies widely from micro to 300
milligrams. And then such wide ranges of
dosing can't be combined for a sensible
analysis. I I strongly disagree with
that. Um the reason for that is because
uh some of the studies that use micro
doses so trace doses like micrograms did
find effect. So we can't have it both
ways right we can't say oh well these
aren't sensible doses
and we want to find an effective lithium
but some of the studies that used such
tiny doses did find an effect of
lithium. So, do we include them or do we
not include them? I say we include them.
If if none of those studies, if every
single study that used micro do
micrograms
uh showed no effect, then you could make
the argument of okay, well, maybe they
weren't using a high enough dose, which
is perfectly plausible. However, uh
considering there were studies that did
find an effect, we can't make that
argument, right? So, I disagree there.
I see no reason to disregard the
positive findings of the Harvard study
and
also mentioned
that
micro doses of lithium oritate had the
previously proposed benefits.
Okay, so this was a continuous critique.
I had many people the Robert is not the
only one um that mentioned that this
Harvard study the the nature study
in no situation
do we take a pre-clinical study and
vault over all the clinical evidence the
clinical the hierarchy of evidence
according to the scientific like every
scientific website every scientific
organization is obviously meta analysis,
the randomized control trials, etc.,
etc. It creates that pyramid. Now, you
could you could haggle a little bit on
like a poorly done meta analysis versus
a really well done randomized control
trial, then maybe the randomized control
trial would take over, right?
But
in no situation, the preclinical data is
like near the bottom. In no situation do
we ever take a pre-clinical study and
over and and take that over a randomized
control trial especially and probably
I'll even I'll limit it to not in any
sort of actionable terms. Okay? And that
has been true for all of my analyses. If
I ever cover pre-clinical data, if I
ever cover pre-clinical data, I'm always
going to state like, hey, this is
preclinical or this is early research or
this is suggestive or you know, words
like that because
if I
say if I start like mixing this evidence
hierarchy of like, oh, clinical data,
yeah, whatever, they said that, but this
preclinical study
showed incredible benefits in a mouse.
So that should vault over like that.
You're you're getting into really
dangerous territory there. So I
while so I'll frame it this way.
The clinical trials that have used
lithium have not used lithium oritate.
And that was another critique that I
received. People were like, "Wow, why
are you even wasting your time looking
at lithium trials that use uh a version
of lithium that was not shown to be
effective in this nature study like
lithium carbonate, lithium gluconate,
glucate uh and sulfate."
And my response is, well, there's no
clinical trials on orate. So unless So
orate is just like wishes and hopes and
dreams at this point. We have one study,
a pre-clinical study indicating that it
may be the superior form of lithium. And
I acknowledge that and I'm not I'm not
going to say that lithium oritate has no
potential, but we're not basing
recommendations and we're not basing
future
uh movement or future actions based on
potential, right? Like if you want to as
an individual that's fine but me when
I'm communicating to to thousands of
people I cannot say oh yeah you should
be using lithium oritate because of this
one nature preclinical study. That's not
how this works. I have to report what
the clinical studies say and I have to
point out what weaknesses and what
strengths there are. Now here's where
people would argue and I have a rebuttal
for this too. Some people said, "Well,
uh you should at least mention uh
lithium oritate
and
because
the the lithium salts the other lithium
salts have been shown have been shown to
be ineffective." Okay, now this is also
incorrect.
Okay, so I just want to be clear here on
multiple fronts. people are like pushing
back, but there's multiple lines of
evidence that they're incorrect.
So, the reason why I focused on the
salts is not just because the clinical
trials use those,
but because
several studies did show an effect of
lithium using those quote unquote
outdated or incorrect versions of
lithium. So, how do we explain that?
Multiple clinical trials show benefit of
using lithium salts, not lithium
oritate.
So, do we just like ignore that? Do we
like close our eyes and just kind of
hope they go away or or do we maybe
acknowledge that just because this
nature study found that lithium oritate
is a
could potentially be a a superior
version of lithium doesn't mean that the
other forms of lithium have no impact.
Can we acknowledge that that's true? And
if that's the case, then the actionable
steps that we have currently based on
the current evidence, the strongest
evidence we have is in the lithium
salts, not lithium oritate. So while I
understand the frustrations,
I think that those frustrations are
based on a thought process that's ahead
of where the evidence actually lies.
And I think that's just it's important
to communicate that effectively. So I'll
communicate it effectively right now. We
have multiple trials,
human trials
that show lithium salts
are effective as lithium
against Alzheimer's disease.
We have one preclinical study that shows
that lithium oritate may be superior to
those lithium salts. We have no clinical
evidence up to now
proving that lithium oritate is superior
to those other salts so far. It is
possible that in the future and probably
very likely in the future we will get a
clinical study that will look at lithium
oritate against Alzheimer's disease. Or
even better would be lithium oritate
versus lithium carbonate
versus
some other forms of lithium other
lithium salts against Alzheimer's
disease. So we can actually have that
comparison across uh different types.
That would be brilliant. But that's
where we stand now. So I think that my
conclusion, my analysis was correct. And
I just don't want to jump the gun to
lithium oritate without at least
mentioning, hey, we don't have any human
evidence of that yet. So if you choose
to use lithium oritate, I don't see
anything inherently wrong with that. But
just know that whatever doses you're
using are based off of the lithium salts
that are not orate. Okay? All right. So
just wanted to address that uh because
it's again it's just important to me. It
just matters when people, you know, have
this like strong reaction against some
of my work. I want to make sure that
people are clear. I I'm not just
willy-nilly just throwing information
out there. I've I've thought this stuff
out and I have arguments to defend my
stances on uh on everything or at the
very least almost everything. So, there
you have it. All right. The final topic
that I'm going to cover in this podcast
before we get into um some of the
housekeeping stuff that I wanted to talk
about and a positive note that I'd like
to discuss as well is vitamin K against
cardiovascular disease.
This is a topic I've been asked to cover
uh for I don't know maybe nine months
now, 10 months, maybe almost a year at
this point. And I I knew that it was
going to be a topic that people were
really interested in. So I paid special
attention and I tried to pull together
every study that I could find uh on the
outcomes
that I defined. Those outcomes are
three. So one
arterial plaque. So the impact that has
on vitamin K has on on arterial plaque.
Number two, the impact that vitamin K
has on calcified plaque and number three
on overall cardiovascular health or
cardiovascular disease.
And so I pulled together I think 30
studies.
I found a systematic review and a and a
meta analysis.
And I pulled all I pulled all those
studies as well. And
overall,
I was pretty blown away by how
confidently
a lot of people on social media discuss
vitamin K. Now, before I go on, one of
the critiques, which I I think is
perfectly fair, one of the critiques
that was levied against me was that I
didn't mention the type of vitamin K.
And to defend myself a little bit, I did
mention it. uh the distinct the type of
my vitamin K. I actually mentioned it 11
times. I measured it or I counted in my
analysis because I I was like paranoid.
Did I really not mention it? But I
mentioned it 11 times to defend the
people that that said that I didn't
mention it. I didn't mention it until
later on in the analysis. So, should I
have mentioned it earlier? Yes. Uh so
I'll say it now. Primarily vitamin K2.
primarily vitamin K2 MK7 variant. Okay,
so that is the one MK7 vitamin K2 is the
one that on social media
so many people have talked about like
it's the the thing that's going to stop
calcified plaque. It's the thing that's
going to reverse plaque. It's the thing
that is going to help against
cardiovascular disease.
And
after analyzing these 30 studies,
was it 30 studies? No, it was 20
studies. Excuse me. Fake news. 20
studies. I'm getting that confused with
another analysis, which is a major one
that I'm
trying to motivate myself to do. It's on
statins, and I have 30 studies uh put
together for that one. Uh I may I'm
hoping to do a full study analysis on
that which is like multi-hour analysis
opening up all the studies to show
people the data. Anyway, it's beside the
point. So vitamin K these 20 studies
after I opened up these 20 studies went
through them
like I said in my analysis I was really
blown away by how confident people are
because when they're talking about
vitamin K2 MK7
because
the majority of the studies show no
effect. Now, I want you like if you
haven't seen my analysis and you just
heard that,
would you be shocked? Are you shocked by
that? Are you surprised at least by
that? Because
there are like almost every video that I
saw online was pointing out, oh, vitamin
K is like you have to take it because
it's so good for your arteries. It's so
good for cardiovascular health. I've got
it to on my supplement stack. all these
different things
and yet and even in in like conference
presentations and whatnot,
I will see like isolated studies of
vitamin K2
against cardiovascular disease or like
calcification of plaque or whatnot,
but those same presentations don't
mention that there are six other studies
that show there's no effect.
I don't know about you, but like if I
and this was true. I think it was like
two studies showed an effect for one of
the outcomes. I forgot which one. It was
either arterial plaque or calcified
plaque and then like six studies showed
no effect.
I mean, at what point do we say like,
"Huh,
should I really be focusing on these two
studies that show an effect while not
mentioning that the vast majority of the
studies showed no effect? How is that
responsible communication?
Can somebody explain that to me? That
doesn't make sense."
So,
anyway, I I tried to find some
throughine. So, I looked at my usual
things. I tried to separate things by
sex. I tried to look at things by
weight, like people who are overweight.
I looked at things by diabetes risk or
metabolic syndrome in general. And there
isn't really a clear through line.
uh
and all of them or almost all of them
like I'll say 80% if not 90% of the
randomized control trials used vitamin
K2 MK7 that everybody talks about on
social media. Oh, that's the version
that you need. But what I also did is I
looked at vitamin K1. So I looked at
vitamin K1, I looked at vitamin K2, I
looked at different versions of vitamin
K2 with obviously MK7 being the the
major one. And it's just all over the
place. The data is just all over the
place. Now, you could argue maybe the
dosing wasn't enough. You could argue
that it wasn't the trial length wasn't
long enough. The the number of
participants wasn't enough. That's fine.
That's all fair. But my point isn't to
say that vitamin K definitely doesn't
work. My point is that on social media
we talk about things so clearly and so
confidently
and yet
there's many studies that show that that
is not the case. So, I just think that
we need to take a step if not multiple
steps back and
communicate that clearly like, hey, it's
possible that vitamin K2 may work and
that's what I mentioned in my analysis
that it might work for people that are
otherwise kind of in unhealthy state as
in they're dealing with diabetes,
they're dealing with metabolic syndrome,
then there were a few studies that
showed and largely those were the
studies that showed an effect. Was that
universal? No, it wasn't. It's possible
that the dose wasn't high enough. I
think the dose was up to 300 400
micrograms, something like that. Don't
quote me on exactly that amount, but
it's somewhere in that realm.
And then a critique that people offered
was, well, studies
studies never use the high enough dose
to to to find an effect. Well, then
where are we getting this information on
social media?
Because how can we have presentations
where we mention that vitamin K2 is
effective
against cardiovascular disease and then
we offer doses.
And yet there are many other studies
that use the same doses and they don't
show an effect. Like there's something
we're missing here. There has to be
something we're missing here. But the
fact that nobody communicates that is
just mind-blowing to me.
So anyway, yeah, for for reversing
arterial plaque, there was almost no
evidence to indicate that was true. I
think the four studies or so that looked
at it, uh,
at least three of them showed no effect.
The calcified plaque, there was a maybe
a little bit more evidence or at least
more studies and still the majority of
studies showed no effect.
Then I went to cardiovascular health as
a whole and there we can't rely on
randomized control trials. In those
situations
I that's where I specifically broke out
vitamin K1 from vitamin K2. Vitamin K1
loses its relationship with
cardiovascular health as in improving
cardiovascular health if you are
accounting for vegetable intakes.
Vitamin K1 is primarily found in uh in
vegetables or in greens and whatnot. So
when you account for vegetable intake or
green intake then you lose that
beneficial relationship between vitamin
K1 and um and cardiovascular health. So
most likely what that indicates is that
if you eat greens that that is the real
benefit or maybe vitamin K1 has some
benefit but it's through the the it's at
least masked by the fact that you're
consuming greens in general. Okay. So
that's fine, right? Fine. Now the more
import the one that everybody goes crazy
about is vitamin K2. And for that one,
uh, there was it's still kind of noisy,
like the the studies weren't as well
done, but there's one study that
accounted for calcium intake as a proxy
for some of the foods that contain uh
vitam vitamin K2. And even when
accounting for calcium, although the the
relationship did weaken,
it was uh still statistically
significant. So that indicates to me
that most likely there is still a
benefit of vitamin K2 independent of
other factors. Now am I really rock
solid on that? No. Because the again the
studies were weaker. So we're talking
about studies that are measuring
nutrition at baseline and then not
measuring it again over like 15 years or
20 years or whatever. Uh, and
look, there's other weaknesses as well,
like they didn't account for a bunch of
different factors. Some of them didn't
account for overall nutrition. Some of
them don't account for physical
activity. Some of them don't. Like,
there's a bunch of different factors
that they just don't account for. So if
you mix all the studies together where
they do kind of account for each other,
you still get a picture where vitamin K2
may have an independent effect at
reducing cardiovascular disease uh risk,
which is okay, fine. Like cool. So that
was kind of my conclusion. And I was
like, "Look, the randomized control
trials are
like if you think there's rocksolid
evidence, you somebody somebody lied to
you." Uh, and if you look at the
totality of evidence across 20 studies,
including a systematic review, which
came to the conclusion that we do not
have strong evidence or we don't have
good evidence for vitamin K, and they
were primarily looking at vitamin K2.
Then
my conclusion after 20 studies is like
we've got some evidence overall that
vitamin K2 MK7 is a benefit.
But that evidence is on shaky ground as
in we need better evidence uh to be
really sure.
And I think that's a reasonable take
considering that the majority of
intervention studies show no effect.
So
my conclusion that there may still be a
benefit if with long-term consumption of
elevated vitamin K2
is I think a pretty bold one considering
that the intervention studies don't show
an effect. Again, those intervention
studies are focused on arterial plaque,
calcified plaque, and then the long-term
studies over decades are looking at
overall cardiovascular health or
cardiovascular disease. So, they're
slightly different. They're measuring
slightly different things. Okay. So the
mechanism by which vitamin K is supposed
to work or one of them at least related
to calcification is one it has a role in
coagulation
which
yeah actually I'll be addressing that in
a little bit as well.
So in the coagulation cascade so like um
like different uh clot formation and and
stuff like that which is a normal
process that we have to have then
vitamin K is involved in that. The other
uh one is that it allows for what's
known as caroxilation. So it's
essentially a specific type of tag
that's applied to a protein called a
matrix gala protein. I forgot what the
gal stands for. It's a particular amino
acid. um
yeah I can't remember the exact amino
acid but it's an amino acid and this
this caroxile tag gets applied to it and
that process of adding the caroxile tag
includes vitamin K. So vitamin K leads
to more of this activated matrix glo
protein. And this protein binds to uh
the calcified sections or the
calcification
molecule called hydroxy appatite
that gets deposited by our cells into
our blood vessels which leads to this
calcification. So the matrix glo protein
physically interacts with that so that
it inhibits that process. So now we
don't get nearly as much calcification.
So it protects us from calcification.
A quick point here that you should ask
yourself though is that do you really
want to inhibit calcification
if the alternative is that you are you
have more soft plaque which is more
related to cardiovascular disease. And
that's something people should really be
thinking about. But in the end, uh even
though it is true and I showed multiple
lines of evidence that vitamin K does
lead to more of this activated uh this
glop protein matrix glop protein mgp.
uh it did not ultimately yield many
convincing data that uh the
calcification process itself would be
impeded by uh vitamin K.
Okay, so that's my spiel on vitamin K.
Now to some comments. Again, some push
back from people. And I'm actually going
to be doing a I'm going to be reading my
response to one of these comments as
well because I had the time to sit there
and think about it as well. So Brian WC
said, "I don't like how you don't
differentiate K1 versus K2 more strongly
in the information presented. The video
is unlike you. It's confusing because
you're often just saying vitamin K
versus specifically distinguishing
vitamin K1 and K2. Such as at the end
where you say vitamin K can increase the
risk of internal bleeding.
It's only K1 that increases that risk.
I'm surprised that you are not more
precise with your language in this
video. The functional medicine doctors
in my area have had incredible success
reducing arterial plaque in lots of
patients by having people take vitamin
K2, magnesium, and nattokinise. Of
course, adding high amounts of soluble
fiber and digestible digestive
resistance starch also helps.
I've seen the data from some of these
local PA patients. I've seen people's
CAC scores, so that's the coronary
artery calcium score, go down after
adding these supplements. There is quite
a bit of clinical data out there that's
not necessarily standard RCT, so
randomized control trials, but it's
still useful when analyzing the newest
edge of available data. Most of your
videos are home run, but as a scientist,
I know that you can handle critical
feedback. Lol. We appreciate we all
appreciate you. So, first of all, Brian,
thank you. I I do appreciate it. Again,
I'm not above critique. Like that's
fine, you know? Critique me as you will,
but and that that was a very polite and
uh just like here's here's my argument.
Cool. Like I I will I will never have
any problems with somebody presenting
that kind of argument. I do take a
little uh I do get a little frustrated
when people question my work and then
they don't p they don't address the
data.
Uh and Brian, I'm not trying to like
specifically single you out. Um because
I I get this just in general. Uh people
will say, "Well, I don't agree with you.
You didn't do a very good job." And that
bothers me. You didn't do a very good
job. But then
it would bother me a lot less and it
would actually make me like really think
about things a lot more if people said
you didn't do a very good job because
you missed this this and this from the
data that you presented and or here are
some additional data. I think that you
should address this. That is an argument
I cannot fight against or I can fight
against it but like it would have to be
a a conversation like a good faith
conversation of okay wow I didn't see
that data before uh that changes things
um oh I can explain that by you know
because this study used this or whatever
it might be but at least then we're
having a discussion of the data as
opposed to just saying well you just
didn't do a very good job and it wasn't
you didn't use very precise language
anguage, which to be fair in the first
half of my analysis, that's true. I I
should have distinguished between K1 and
K2. I was talking primarily about K2
throughout that part. It wasn't until
later that I um that I really broke up
the two. Okay. But I ended up uh adding
a response
and
I end up saying that sure, you're right.
I'm happy to take feedback so long as
the feedback is correct, which it isn't
in this case. And considering that
you're claiming that this video is
unlike my usual work, I'll defend my
work against your word. So, number one,
both vitamin K1 and vitamin K2 are
implicated in the clotting cascade and
are hazard when consumed with
bloodrelated drugs.
And this is where I took a little bit of
um of liberty here with uh Brian because
Brian specifically said that
I'm surprised that you are not more
precise with your language in this
video.
And
Brian conveniently uh left out some of
the precise language that I used in my
video. uh which again just speaks to
like if we're going to have a discussion
we have to be we have to be good faith
with one another and we have to uh
present each other's arguments
completely and fairly. So, in my video,
my what my actual argument was, hey, at
the end I mentioned if you're if you are
going to be supplementing, if you decide
to supplement with vitamin K, K1 or K2
doesn't matter, then you should uh
definitely think about it even more as
in think about not doing it even more if
uh you are on uh blood clotting
medications like warrin or whatever it
might be. And the reason for that is
because it, like I said, it's involved
in the clotting cascade. And unlike what
Brian said, it is not just vitamin K1
that has that warning. In fact, if you
go to the NIH website, if you go to
Medline, uh they mention vitam they
explicitly say vitamin K1, vitamin K2,
vitamin K3. So, all forms of vitamin K
because even though they're not exactly
integrated in the same steps, they are
integrated in this whole clotting
cascade and they can interfere with that
process. So it is a risk. So something
that you know everybody who's
supplementing with any form of vitamin K
should be aware of and that's why I
mentioned that it's specific to people
who are taking these drugs. Okay? So I
and I mentioned that in the video uh
which Brian left that out.
So to say that I'm imprecise with my
language but then mischaracterizing what
I actually said is again I I'm not like
saying anything um I'm not saying this
was on purpose or anything like that but
I I do think that
when people come to me and they've got
critiques and it's like wellfounded
critiques I am
I get really frustrated with myself uh
when I mess something up and I
immediately try to jump on it and try to
correct it and of course give that
person credit. Um, but what I also
what I also really think is important is
that I defend my work. And when I don't
think that a person is being fair about
how they're representing my work, it
does bother me because
if people just read that comment,
then they think that, oh, Nick isn't
being precise or Nick isn't a good
source for reputable information. and my
integrity and my
just my the the the work that I put out
there.
I'm constantly trying to improve it
because yeah, my integrity just means so
much to me and putting out good
information, great information is of the
utmost importance to me. So when
somebody points out that I made
mistakes, I jump on them like where
where tell me how like where did I make
a mistake so I can I can correct it. But
if somebody says, "Well, you made a
mistake and I just feel this way." And
then they are mischaracterizing my
perspective.
That's I mean, I have to defend myself.
It's just it's I just don't consider it
right. So number two, you mentioned
functional doctors have had success and
that's fine, but that isn't scientific
evidence. Second to that, by your own
comment, they used multiple
interventions. So remember uh by Brian's
point
mentioned that
uh they used
vitamin K, they use magnesium and
nattokinus and then later also mentioned
soluble fiber and digestive uh
resistance starches.
So now we're talking about three, four,
five different things being used at the
same time. And let's say let's assume
that those people did have arterial
plaque reversal.
How in the world can we attribute that
to vitamin K? The better evidence, the
randomized control trials that look at
the the matter against a placebo group
show no effect. So why would I suddenly
take a
let's say multiple anecdotes even in a
clinical setting that have no control
group
that use five different interventions at
the same time and then say aha vitamin K
that's the thing that worked. That
doesn't work. That's not that's not a
scientific way to approach uh the
evidence.
Uh, number three, I've seen people's CAC
score go down after adding these
supplements. Again, this is anecdote.
Limitless factors could confound that
result.
Okay. And then number four, there's
quite a bit of clinical data out there.
That's what Brian said. And I all I said
was just provide some. I provided 20
studies. That's not necessarily standard
RCTs. That's what Brian said. Okay. So,
I provide gold standard evidence. and in
in addition look at long-term data as
well as a systematic review actually
technically two so along the hierarchy
of evidence I've hit all three pillars
so that systematic review at the top
randomized control trials and then the
epidemiological evidence after that and
of course you can have a little bit of
mixture between them depending on the
quality of each so I've hit all three uh
all three pillars I'm happy to look at
more evidence but you're self you are
self-proclaiming that the evidence is
not as rigorous because Brian admitted
which was uh which was good that the
clinical evidence is not going to be up
to par of the RCTs. So the entire
argument is based off of anecdote
clinical settings where multiple
interventions are used and what even if
there was like the best possible
clinical data none of that has is
controlled none of that takes into
account uh like randomization
uh placebo control nothing so it's it's
going to be lower quality evidence
regardless of how you how you slice it
um and then I that again I appreciate
the feedback to improve which I always
do. Uh but I can't just accept feedback
without justified push back if I think
and proven that I've done my work
properly. And that's really important to
me. I just it like I feel like I really
have to communicate that uh multiple
times over because it it matters so much
to me that I'm willing to back down from
positions as long as I'm presented with
information data specifically not
information data uh that is rigorously
controlled that you know where I've
missed particular aspects and in that
situation yes I will definitely issue
corrections do whatever I need to do um
but I I just can't have people and
people often do this. They just feel
that I've done something wrong or
they've got clinical data or they know
the brother of my aunt of I was going to
say brother of my aunt. Well, that would
be your uncle then. Or yeah, that would
be your uncle or maybe even your dad. Um
the the I don't know the the
the lawn care guy of my aunt started
taking vitamin K and his anga his chest
pains went away like okay I mean that
good like I'm glad but that doesn't that
doesn't prove anything to me that's not
evidence to me. Okay. Anyway, domac48
said, "My problem with scientific
studies of supplements is that they seem
to use the smallest dose possible and
then say that it doesn't do anything."
Okay, so I kind of addressed that
earlier, right? Um,
let's assume that that's true,
that the scientific studies, which by
the way, some of the studies that showed
an effect use the same dose as some of
the studies that showed no effect. Okay.
So that's one very important point.
So let's assume
that
the studies don't show an effect.
And yet on social media we have health
influencers
that will point to the study that did
show an effect and say that's the dose
to use. And yet they ignore the other
study that used the exact same dose if
not potentially higher. and
still say that this one dose is the one
that has scientific evidence behind it.
Or even worse in my estimation is they
just make up a number. They just say,
"Okay, 300 micrograms
uh showed some effect. Let's double it.
600."
In that situation, you just have a
person talking versus studies that show
there's no effect. So again, like it's
it's kind of a riskbenefit
uh situation, but me, I tend to be
pretty conservative. I'm not as
conservative as some physicians uh
where, you know, they they only focus on
drugs or they only focus on exercise or
they only focus on nutrition, which is
fine. Um and certainly I do as well, but
I go just a little bit beyond that. But
then there are people that go leaps and
bounds beyond that where they just kind
of throw out numbers and they're like,
"Well, my functional medicine
guru or whatever, some health influencer
said uh that you actually have to take
triple what the studies show and that's
why it's underdosed." It's like based on
what evidence do they have any
pharmaccoinetics? Do they have any sort
of data to to indicate that that's the
case? They're just saying it. They're
literally just saying it. By the way,
omega-3s are not effective at 1 or 4 g.
What's actually effective is 10,000
trillion billion kg of omega-3s.
Don't ask me for evidence. I I tried it
on one of my one of my clients and it
worked. Like that's not evidence. That's
just that's a scary situation to be
telling people that that's what's that's
what's going to work. So, and also do I
do I I mean you may feel different. You
listening to this, you may feel
different, but my impression is that
scientists aren't out there designing
studies that they know are going to
fail. You understand that a scientist
doesn't get funding anymore if they
continuously release studies that don't
show an effect. And not to mention,
they're going to get under more scrutiny
for future grants. Uh, so I just find it
hard to believe that these these
scientists are like, "Okay, let's let's
let's put a year or two years worth of
work into this vitamin K study, but
let's figure out a way for it not to
show an effect."
Like, what?
Who would do that? And not to mention,
it's not one group. It's like 10
different research labs. They're all
doing it. they're all underdosing.
Like there's a reason why they go for
these particular doses. There's
preclinical data. There's there's
pharmaccoinetic data. There's all kinds
of other types of data that indicate
that's the dose that you should be
using. And then studies if they see kind
of marginal benefits, maybe they'll be
like, okay, let's try increasing that
for a future investigation. Let's try to
increase the sample size. Let's try to
do different. Let's elongate the study.
Like they're always adapting. Like
scientists aren't doing research just to
find null results to me that just seems
it's just kind of out there. I I mean
could it happen? Yeah. But could it
happen across the entire scientific
field? I just I don't think so.
And again, maybe you feel differently.
Okay. William Boquist said,
"I think in my video I said, I think
you'll find these results are sobering."
And William said, "Good. I'll bookmark
this video and watch it again when I'm
hammered and have work to do."
So, yeah, that was a good one. And then
I I'm gonna I'm gonna I'm going to rant
a little bit longer. hopefully you'll
indulge me
that I also get these comments of people
that just kind of treat me like I'm a
kid and I just don't I don't know uh you
know right from wrong and I I'm still
stuck in the establishment and I I don't
have
I don't have the the world experience to
be able to speak on some of these topics
and like fine whatever but
there there were a few comments one of
them I find really funny because of who
uh sent it. But one comment said uh BD
Cochran01. This was this was perfectly
fine comment, but just kind of in that
same vein, which I get a lot of these.
Uh I'm old enough to be your
grandfather. Therefore, I relate some
things to bear in mind. One,
everything that I learned in college 60
years ago has been proven wrong,
superseded, or has become nuanced.
Actually,
that sounds pretty good. That sounds
like progress to me. Uh, especially the
last one. If it's become nuanced, I love
that. Uh, two, if you condition yourself
to question your assumptions and your
indoctrination, you will be ahead in
life before most people.
Okay. I I don't I think people don't
understand like what goes into a PhD. I
mean, the whole thing is just questions,
right? questions and then you go find
the answer and they give you money, they
give you resources and then you get some
guidance from a a a PI, your your mentor
and they tell you, okay, go, you know,
do try the experiments, try to figure
out the answer.
Uh, three, do your own research.
In the old days, I had to go to the
medical library and struggle to find
information. Now, you can use your home
computer. That's true. That's that's
definitely true. I mean, uh, the
internet has opened up so much and I I
completely agree with that. Um,
and number four, always value facts over
the truth.
The first is objective and the second
option is subjective.
I don't I mean, honestly, I don't I
probably have to think about that one
some more. I don't fully understand that
one. And I I did end up commenting. I
said, uh, I appreciate the comment, but
I'm very confused as to how this relates
to the topic. This was under my vitamin
K analysis.
And then somebody else responded, which
I'll get to, but like do your own
research. This is something that's kind
of become a a mainstay for a lot of
people. Just do your own research. But
if I can hearken back real quick to
somebody else who commented in one of
the previous analysis that we went over
for glycine, Sabrina,
remember how Sabrina said, uh, I am
truly confused. I thought glycine was an
anti-cancer, anti-aging, antioxidant.
Then she goes on and so on and so forth.
But she says, "The more I quote unquote
educate myself, the more I feel that I
have no idea what's going on." Okay. So,
that's where I think I think this um
this kind of uh
I don't know what to call it, but this
almost anti-expertise
kind of mentality of well, I can't trust
other people. I can't trust experts in a
field uh because you know whatever it
might be because one day they say one
thing or another day they say something
else or maybe the establishment is
compromised or whatever it might be. I I
I don't know. It doesn't really matter.
The the point being that we can't trust
experts like we're we're kind of getting
into this this world of like we just
have to educate ourselves. We just have
to do it ourselves. We have to do our
own research.
And I gotta be honest with you, how are
you going to do your own research if you
don't know how to read the controls on a
western blot or if you don't understand
how to how HLC is done or how mass spect
mass spectrometry is done or like how
are you going to you don't know how the
experiments are done that gave you the
data that you are then having to analyze
not to mention then you have to run it
through statistics and understand how
statistics work. Like that takes work.
It's like, you know, during my PhD, I
didn't just like twiddle my thumbs. Like
I was educated obviously on the the
general stuff, right? I I went through
the whole all the body systems. I went
from the from the molecular level up to
the whole the whole physiological level
and it was grueling.
But what I was also taught for for
threearters of my education was about
the experiments. We had to learn how
they worked. We had to
understand
how to piece together experiments to get
a particular result because sometimes
you have to do multiple experiments just
to get to a result to get a result.
uh we were given questions and then
asked okay now you have to design an
experiment based off of this uh we want
to know the answer to this like this is
the question this is the scenario now
you design the experiments to to allow
us to do that and this was in neur
neuroscience this was in cancer research
this was in uh gastroenterenterology
like we did everything all the way
across
and that's our job. Like that's what
PhDs do. They analyze research. They
they they do research. They actually
physically sit there and do research.
They think about it. They plan it. They
pipet. They do the actual experiments.
They they put together like actual
experimental uh methods
and then they get the output, right? And
then they have to uh do an analysis on
the output. So they have to run
statistics and then they have to sit
there and think about what that output
actually means.
and they have to then broaden that to
the overall context of the entire uh
paper that they want to publish.
So to me like do your own research
is
I think it's it's pretty treacherous
because if you have no concept of how
any of that stuff works like do your own
research is like reading Sanskrit. Like
I I don't know how to read Sanscripts. I
would just be like I I don't know what
I'm looking at.
I mean, is age going to make a
difference in that? No. Is is anything
going to make a difference other than
just experience? Just having been
exposed and being taught by somebody who
knows more than you do on the topic.
That's what's that's what you have to
do. Um so yeah, this do your own
research thing. I've heard it a lot and
I've definitely heard it against me uh
for sure where people have have claimed
their age. I'm this many years old. Uh
you're young, you don't understand. And
you know that's fine. Like I think in
life I think that's a really good point.
I'm relatively young. Um and as a result
I have less experience than uh many
other people that may be 20 years my
senior. Cool. And I completely
acknowledge that. I'm not here to like
be delusional or anything like that, but
I think when it comes to science, at
least like at the very least analyzing
studies,
I'm not going to say I'm like the best
or anything like that. And I still have
plenty of work to do and I will always
continue to work at it. But I would say
in that topic I have I have more
experience than a lot of people
especially people that don't have a PhD
because that is what a PhD is. Uh on the
other hand you know
if you talk to me about like people that
study uh micro gleal damage after
I post-traumatic
uh brain disorder whatever I'm just
making. something up then those people
would have more experience than I do
even if they're let's say 28 years old
because they've had maybe two three five
years of research experience in that
area right so experience is not just
based on the overall breadth of
experience of just being alive it's also
based on how you focus your attention
what do you focus your attention on so
again this like do your own research.
It's I don't know. I think it's a
dangerous road to go down. But then
again, I also don't want people to feel
unempowered. I do want people to feel
empowered to
to do a little bit of background reading
on their own and to push their doctors
and to push me and push other people
that are are relating this information
because you do want to test and you want
to ask questions and you want to be
curious and it goes back to one of my
previous points of I do love engaging
with people that are curious and want to
know more and because that's how I am
too when it comes to to my field. Um,
so yeah, it's it's a delicate balance,
but anyway, thank you for the for the
comment, BD. I appreciate it. Now, one,
like I said, I said I appreciate the
comment, but I'm very confused how this
relates to the topic. Socrates had
something to say, which I I I find very
funny. Socrates uh very famous
philosopher
um
around the same time I think he was the
tutor of Plato if I remember correctly.
So Socrates said you proved the you
proved his point. I'm confused how
you're confused. Uh they're talking
about how to take take in information
and not become dogmatic but to stay open
and use uh discernment and to rely on
facts not bias. and you don't know how
to how that relates to interpreting
interpreting scientific data, which is
what you present every week.
Yeah. Again, it's just it's kind of the
same argument, right? Um
like this idea that
we're becoming dogmatic and and whatnot.
And some people are for sure. Um and
then, you know, I got I got others like
who do you work for? And like
I've been compromised by uh by the the
the industry. I've been compromised by
big I don't know. I I don't know who. I
don't know. I mean my conclusion again
for this this analysis was vitamin K2
probably works. I'm leaning towards it
working. Is it going to have a dramatic
effect? Probably not. Uh and the
evidence is shaky and we need more
evidence. So, if that makes me dogmatic
after presenting my evidence,
again, I I just want people to just
uh present data. That's really all I
really care about. Um, so I think I've
said it enough. I I won't go down that
road again. Okay.
I want to get into some housekeeping. I
keep that till the end because I know
people don't uh aren't always that
interested in it. Uh but I wanted to
leave things on some positive notes. Uh
I get a lot of critique but I also get a
lot of encouragement
and I deeply deeply appreciate that. It
really does mean a lot to me. Um
so you know like uh Physionic has it
definitely doesn't grow very quickly. Um
it's not a channel that's that's like
exploding or anything along those lines.
And I don't really care. I don't care if
it does or if it doesn't. Um, would it
be nice to have like huge growth? Of
course. Like, who doesn't want that? But
I also don't want it to be um I don't
want it to be get to a point where it's
unmanageable. And uh I do want to keep
physionic small, just me. Um, and it's
fun and that's that's important and it
helps people. Um, I get a lot of
comments and a lot of messages from
people saying how much my work has
helped them and I I mean that that means
the world to me honestly. It's just like
it's it's it's very very fulfilling in
that regard. Um, and it it motivates me
further. Again, not that I ever needed
extra motivation, but it motivates me
further to continue to release uh
intellectually honest information, which
again means that sometimes I have to own
up if I get something incorrect and
correct it. Uh, and on the other hand,
also to defend myself whenever I think
that I've done a good job.
So yeah, it's uh it's been it's been
slowgoing, but it's growing. And uh I
I'm always incredibly appreciative of
the fact that I have even a small number
of people that care about the work that
I put out there. And I get comments, I
get emails, and I get messages
uh every day. And it's I I can't keep up
with all of it, but I do I just want you
to know that if you've ever sent me a
message or a comment or anything like
that, even if I haven't necessarily read
it, I just want you to know I deeply do
appreciate it. It it means the world to
me. Um
beyond that
and just the fact that I get to get to
do this independent of any sponsorships.
I think like two years ago, I was really
wrestling with the idea because I I've
I've received at least 300 sponsorship
requests on my website. I have for the
messaging before people send me an
email, I have a note that says, "Do not
contact me." If you are trying to pitch
me a CEO to be on Physionic, if you're
trying to pitch me some researchers
that's selling their supplement or
whatever to be on Physionic. If you are
trying to sell your new magnesium
glyphonate, I don't know, I'm just
making something up. Uh 3000, I don't
care. Just don't even bother contacting
me. And I've still been contacted
hundreds of times from people trying to
get me to uh to
like for them to sponsor a segment on
Physionic. And I remember about 2 years
ago, I asked you guys, I asked you
how you would see me if I did take
sponsorships. Uh so if I did like
sponsored segments and whatnot.
And honestly, I think the majority of
people said that they didn't care. It
wouldn't have bothered them. And there
was a small number of people, I'd say
maybe 20%, 30% maybe, that said it would
probably shift their perspective. And of
course, you know, it's it's a biased
sample because people that are going to
click on the video, they're going to
offer their opinion,
the people that are going to say, "Oh,
it wouldn't bother me." That's probably
because they already trust me. But what
I'm also trying to do is make sure that
the perception
of
having outside influences is something
that I'm really trying to push away as
well. Uh so
even though I could have done some
sponsorships with some pretty big
brands, I just chose not to.
And even though the majority of people
were saying it probably wouldn't change
their perspective and it wasn't actually
about the opinions of those people that
uh that changed that lean me towards not
doing sponsorships.
It was actually the people that I
haven't reached yet.
I want to I want to be able to be in a
position where uh I just say, "Oh, I
have no
no one is is dictating anything except
for me and the the I guess called the
crowdsourcing from the insiders." So
to me, it was really important uh that I
keep myself sponsorship free and I will
continue to do that for as long as I
can.
and the fact that I get to do physionic
sponsorship free and I've also uh
stepped back from consulting as well. um
not completely but by a large part and I
get to do what I love which is just
analyze
analyze research to to the end of days
um just constantly be reading research
and to to have fun putting these uh
videos together and the articles and
like all that stuff. And if you're not
familiar, I also release uh multiple
articles per week uh that release on my
email list, the free physionic community
as well. Um I also post them on LinkedIn
and and bunch of other places. So the
fact that I get to do that is just like
it's
it's incredible. And uh again, I I
always end these podcasts I always say
thank you because it it really does mean
a lot to me. I also do these podcasts
only every six months. So, so I just I
want to remind you that I'm continuously
thankful. I just wanted to point that
out. Uh,
okay. So, I did want to leave here with
uh a few more things. One is I had even
though the the comment section can be a
place that's just like full of nonsense,
um I've also had the pleasure of having
a some really funny people comment. You
heard some of them, right? Like the
bourbon joke that we talked about
earlier or or what was the the the the
other one? I forgot. Any Oh, the
sobering one uh about um vitamin K.
But I also have some really great
engagements with people that comment.
And sometimes people will say, you know,
I've never commented before,
but I I needed to say this thing. And so
I I try to like obviously I miss
hundreds and hundreds of comments, but
um I try to respond to to those kinds of
comments because I want people to feel
like uh physionic is a place where they
can actually uh speak and not like not
feel like dumb questions. There are no
dumb questions like
well I mean technically there are dumb
questions like if I say you know is this
phone cover like is this screen black
and it's clearly black I mean I guess
that would be a dumb question but in
general when it comes to scientific
questions related to like biology
physiology nutrition whatnot um it can
be a really basic question I don't but
just because it's a basic question
doesn't make it a dumb
So anyway, this all to say, I'm kind of
talking in circles here, but this all to
say, I had a lovely exchange with
Michael Johnson
that I wanted to read with uh read to
you. Uh Michael Johnson said, "I've been
trying to better my health for a number
of years now. I'm 36 and I have
agorophobia as well as fibromyalgia.
I'm not the most intelligent person in
the sense that I find it genuinely
difficult to differentiate fact from
fiction due to so many quote unquote
experts online. And I'm also not very
successful academically. Kicked out of
school at uh age 15.
There's no such information out there
that I find simply Oh, there is so much
information out there that I find simply
overwhelming. I'm also not the most
well-off person, so finding decent
quality supplements are hard for me. I
try to focus on diet as well as exercise
naturally. I suppose what I'm asking is
how would someone as bewildered and
overwhelmed by such information navigate
this minefield of a subject that is
health and nutrition. Apologies for such
a long message.
Again, I I and that that's why I had
this preamble because I
you understand like a person that's
dealing with agorophobia, fibromyalgia,
and like many other people have
commented about other issues that they
have and to put that out on the internet
and I think it takes takes a a certain
level of uh bravery and I I really every
time anytime I see a comment like that,
I do try to engage because it means a
lot to me going back to what I said at
the beginning. But also,
I just want to recognize and I really
want to tell people that uh
like I hear you and
even though there aren't a ton of
resources out there, there are people
that are trying to do the right thing.
and I've, you know, I've engaged with
them in the past and I will continue to
engage with them uh in the future and
I'll always try to highlight people that
I think are are doing a great job which
I may actually come back to that point
in just a little bit. But let me let me
get to my response. Uh, Michael, if this
is your barometer for your intelligence,
quote, in the sense that I find genuine
find it genuinely difficult to
differentiate fact from fiction due to
so many quote unquote experts online,
then we are all morons. Just by the way
that you write, I can tell that you're
far more intelligent than you give
yourself credit. As for navigating an
information minefield, that's a topic
that that I'm still wrestling with. I
don't have a satisfactory answer. I used
to, but it's had a few holes blown
through it. In my field, it's easy to to
differentiate because I know as much as
they do. However, in other fields, I
also have trouble. I tend to just rely
on the most boring sources. So,
textbooks, uh, releases by research
bodies like universities and and the
like. Or I have a few people that I
trust outside of my field like my dad in
physics. He has a PhD in physics and a
master's in mechanical engineering. So I
asked him on physics concepts,
it's not easy and you are not in any way
less intelligent for not having figured
it out. And then his response was, thank
you for your response. I hope that the
term quote unquote experts in quotation
marks wasn't taken as an insult to
yourself as I do trust you. Thank you,
Michael. No, it was not. Uh I'm sure
you're aware of so many people online
claiming to be someone that they're not.
I do not believe that is the case for
you. Thank you. Uh I'm just extremely
exhausted with everything. I think I
worded my comment in frustration. I just
want you to know that I appreciate all
the work and I hope that we can all find
simpler answers to some of life's
toughest questions. Thank you for
replying to my comment. It means a lot
to me. Yeah. So, I wanted to highlight
this because
that the bigger question that Michael's
asking about this uh
um you know, I'm realizing I'm getting
sunburnt over here. Joy, oh joy, I tried
to escape the sun. Couldn't do it. Uh
the sun hath defeated me. Yeah. I think
the the the bigger point here though,
and it's true like I I used to have
answers, right, for for like who you can
trust, who you can't trust. uh when it
comes to this field of like health and
nutrition and exercise and and whatnot
which are kind of intermingled medicine
and it's become more difficult simply
because I think in the past maybe five
years ago I would have said well the
people that actually provide citations
the ones that actually discuss science
uh that actually you know go into
studies like actually say hey there's
this study and this is what it says is a
pretty good barometer
at least an initial marker that it might
be someone that you could listen to.
Uh, but nowadays what I'm finding is
that there's a lot of I'll just go and
say it, charlatans that that use studies
and they just pick out little phrases
from those studies and then or small
concepts from those studies or
completely butcher the study or they'll
just they they use one study and then
ignore all the rest of the literature
and they make entire videos about it,
you know, where it's like a person
holding a walnut and it's like over some
like green drink or whatever it might be
and
and it's like uh scientists have broken
open the the reality of heart health or
something like that and it has to do
with this and it's just like I don't
know some like obscure study that's just
like out of Russia in 1983. three or
something like that where they gave
walnuts to Labrador dogs or something
like that and and uh they I don't know.
It's just like I you get my point. It's
just like completely obscure and they're
and
it's just so far out there.
But they're technically following what I
used to say, right? like they're using a
study, they're they're flashing the
title of the study, they have
references, maybe they have references
uh in the description,
but that doesn't actually mean that the
study says what they say or in the
context of the literature that that's
actually an appropriate overall
conclusion. And not to mention, it's
like short-term memory loss, right? like
they say one thing on one week, which it
goes back to, you know, one of the major
complaints I was talking about earlier
and then the next week they're talking
about something completely different
that also does the same thing. But they
never take release a video that says
like, "Hey, by the way, I know that I
said that this was the biggest thing and
now I'm saying this is the biggest
thing."
The reality is that you know they both
contribute such a high amount such a
great amount that I you know like and
they start trying to apply context like
what they said they just blast forward
the third week they're like this is the
best thing in the world.
And you do have to take a few uh a few
pages out of their book because if
you're going to fight that fight of like
trying to get good information out
there, you do have to create kind of
like explosive narratives and stuff. But
you're always if you if you are really
trying to put out good scientific
information, you're always going to be
constrained by what the data actually
says. And that's always important. And
there's a there's a Reddit post. I'm on
Reddit a good amount. Uh, I just like to
peruse. I like to to talk with people
that are also in kind of scientific
nutrition and uh that are in the
subreddits and and different biohacking
and whatnot. And plus, there's there's
sometimes really good topics and there's
actually some really good discussion
there sometimes. So,
uh, sometimes being the operative word
there. But there's this one person that
posted my vitamin K, uh, video and and
analysis, and there's this one person
that commented, and I actually really
liked their comment. It was largely
negative against me. But what I really
liked about their comment was that they
said because I responded they they said,
"Look, I I think that your like the
titles and the thumbnails are really
like they seem like they're going to be
a really exciting concept and then I
click on the video and I'm going through
the video and I get bored
because it's not as exciting as I
thought it was going to be." And that's
ah I love that because that's exactly
what I'm trying to do. I'm trying to get
people to be I'm trying to get the right
people. I'm trying to attract people,
right? So I'm using the similar systems
that, you know, people that I don't
think are are trying to do the right
thing.
So, I'll take I'll take like the the
enticing title and the enticing
thumbnail, which of course still have to
be factually accurate. Like, I can't
just, you know, make a video about
cancer and then the whole video is about
cardiovascular disease. Um, but it has
to be accurate. And there's so much
exciting information out in the
scientific literature. It's just how you
frame it that's important. Uh, so the
fact that they would they they were
enticed to click on it. love that
because hopefully it took a view from
someone else that may be covering that
same study but doing potentially a poor
job. But the second thing is that they
were bored. I mean, in in my in my
YouTube analytics and whatnot, it it
shows that people actually stick around
for quite a lot. But the the fact that
this person was describing it as boring,
I think is kind of a point of pride. I'm
not saying that I want to like bore
people's pants off or anything like
that, but their like head falls off
because they're so bored out of their
mind, but what I
but I don't want to come off as like
just another person that's just like
throwing BS at you. Uh so once you click
on the video, to me, I have leeway to to
be like, "Look, I'm going to show you
some really exciting stuff." What that I
think is exciting. this is what the data
shows and I'm going to tell you the
story that's related through the data
and I think that is really fun and and
really exciting
and I don't want people walking away
thinking that like chia seeds are going
to cure their cancer because they're not
you know which is like how the the
follow through for a lot of other
channels and a lot of other um kind of
that
kind uh the health influencer world that
I don't really like very much. Uh they
have that throughine of like I'm I'm
going to blow your mind by focusing on
this teeny tiny thing and not expand
outwards to give you a a a clear picture
of what the data actually shows. Um so I
don't know it's it's navigating a a
minefield. But going back to Michael's
comment just in general it's it's uh I
have not figured it out. I I thought
that I did, like I said, and now it's
become trickier because now you have
everybody that's just relying on
studies, but that doesn't actually
necessarily mean that they are
presenting those studies correctly,
which ultimately leads us back to square
one, right? Um, now we don't know. So,
if you have any uh any input, any
advice, uh I'd be happy to hear. I' I'd
like to I'd like to hear and you know
maybe one day I can I can get a guide
out of like this kind of stepby-step
process. I I have thought about doing
that in the past and I've thought about
reaching out to some of the creators
that I really admire and seeing if we
can maybe put our heads together and see
if we can come up with some sort of like
step-by-step guide. It's not going to be
perfect, obviously, but some sort of
step-by-step guide that people could
just have for free that would help
people navigate. Okay, I'm watching this
video. Here's my three steps I need to
think about. Do they fulfill step one?
Do they fulfill step two? Do they
fulfill step three? And that will give
at least some guidance and hopefully
some ability to to navigate because if
we rely on things like the centrifuge or
I know uh Jill Carvalo uh at nutrition
made simple has some some stuff where he
debunks um particular influencers as
well. If we rely on that, I mean, the
the the speed at which people can
release BS is a million times faster
than we can sit there and fact check and
make sure we're we're being polite and
make sure we're being, you know, uh,
appropriate, like appropriately giving
credit where it's due and then, you
know, correcting where it's due. It's
just, it's going to be impossible. So,
we're going to have to have some sort of
system to to try to tease out some of
those.
Uh, yeah. Anyway, so I just wanted to
end things on a positive note. Um,
I've started upping my Instagram game.
Uh, that's been going surprisingly well.
All I do is just turn on a camera and
just talk about stuff in in far less uh
long- winded format than I did uh in
this podcast.
But, uh, that's been going well.
Surprisingly, I've been, uh, been
pleasantly surprised. I'm trying to just
have fun. Um, and
yeah, just try to try to branch out and
see see what other avenues I can I can
use to to kind of spread the scientific
nerddom in a manner of speaking. Um,
one last thing. I got got a dog. Back
away. back away. Some bumblebee or
something was attacking me ferociously.
Um, yeah, I got a dog. Her name is
Olive. I will uh post a picture if
you're interested. And uh that's that's
my non-scientific, non-physionic news.
Um she's been a joy so far. Definitely
uh enjoying life with with Olive. Um
what else?
I think that's about it. Again, if um if
you're ever so inclined, then uh you can
support me by joining the Physionic
Insiders.
But to be honest with you, do not join
the Physionic Insiders just to support
me. Um I I take extreme pride in the
amount of work that I put into the
insiders. You get podcasts which are far
more succinct than what I have here.
They're just information.
Um,
you get articles, weekly articles,
multiple weekly articles. You get a
private email list. Uh, you get no ads
on any videos, on any articles, nothing.
So, everything gets delivered to your
email inbox. Uh, you get live sessions
with me.
What else do you get? I designed a
Physionic AI. It's not like the best
thing in the world or anything, but it's
it's uh I I taught it based on all of my
work, so it answers based off of my
work. Um, and you get bunch of other
things as well, like one paragraph
summaries with the main key takeaways
that you should uh that you should have.
Oh, master supplement list that I built.
I'm very excited about that. I think
people are really taking advantage of
that. It goes into the supplement. It
goes into the outcome of interest. It
goes into the amount of impact that I
think that that supplement will have and
then uh the dosing obviously and then uh
the different brands that I think are
are good brands. So, and then there's a
few other benefits of being an insider.
But anyway, you don't don't feel any
pressure to join. Um, but for those
insiders that are insiders, uh, people
have messaged me that they're quite
happy with uh the the the
quality of the work that's there, which
I'm I'm deeply appreciative of. Again, I
take a lot of pride in in in how much
work I put into it. So, it means a lot
to me. Anyway, physionic insider or not,
I deeply appreciate you being here. Um,
I know that this was a bit of like, you
know, getting into some of the specifics
of different comments and stuff like
that. And I think that there is I I'm
trying not to be quite as
solely focused on just analysis and
whatnot, but also trying to hear and
understand where people are coming from
and try to answer questions wherever I
can. So, uh, hopefully it was of at
least some benefit. And if you're
asleep, then nighty night. I hope you I
hope you sleep well. Uh thanks again and
uh until next time. Maybe in six months,
maybe in a year, who knows? Till next
time. See you.